<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A way of reconciliation of a good and learned man touching the trueth, nature, and substance of the body and blood of Christ in the sacrament. Translated out of Latin by the right honorable Lady Elizabeth Russell, dowager to the right honourable the Lord Iohn Russell, Baron, and sonne and heire to Francis Earle of Bedford.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 218 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11189</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101217</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837034</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837034</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1338</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11189)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1338)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 974:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A way of reconciliation of a good and learned man touching the trueth, nature, and substance of the body and blood of Christ in the sacrament. Translated out of Latin by the right honorable Lady Elizabeth Russell, dowager to the right honourable the Lord Iohn Russell, Baron, and sonne and heire to Francis Earle of Bedford.</title>
                  <author>Russell, Elizabeth Cooke Hoby, Lady, ca. 1540-1609.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. B[arker],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A way of reconciliation touching the Lords Supper.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Real presence --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1338:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1338:1"/>
            <p>A WAY OF RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CONCILIATION OF A GOOD AND learned man, TOVCHING THE <hi>Trueth, Nature, and Substance</hi> of the Body and Blood of Chriſt in the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Latin into Engliſh by the Right Honorable Lady <hi>Elizabeth Ruſſell,</hi> Dowager to the Right Honourable the Lord <hi>Iohn Ruſſell,</hi> Baron, and ſonne and heire to <hi>Francis</hi> Earle of Bedford.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON PRINTED BY <hi>R. B.</hi> ANNO 1605.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1338:2"/>
            <head>The Author to the Reader.</head>
            <p>TO ſeeke the attonement of men is to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and it hath a ſure promiſe of God: <hi>Bleſſed bee the peace-makers.</hi> But I feare me, leſt in greedily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the ſame, it happen to me which chanceth to them that part fraies, while they ſeeke others ſafetie, they beare the blowes themſelues. And I, while I ſtudy to make enemies friends, perhaps ſhall haue ſmall thankes of them. Which if it happen, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of him ſhal comfort me, which ſaid: <hi>If I ſhould pleaſe men, I ſhould not be the ſeruant of Chriſt.</hi> Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, and indeauour thy ſelfe to pleaſe Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1338:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable my moſt entierly beloued <hi>and onely daughter, the Lady</hi> ANNE HERBERT, wife to the Lord HENRY HERBERT, ſonne and heire apparant to EDVVARD the moſt noble Earle of Worceſter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt vertuous and</hi> woorthilie beloued daughter, Euen as from your first birth and cradle J euer was most careful, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue any worldly thing, to haue you ſucke the perfect milke of ſincere Religion: So willing to ende as I beganne, I haue left to you, as my laſt Legacie, this Booke. A most precious Iewell to the comfort of your Soule, being the woorke of a moſt good,
<pb facs="tcp:1338:3"/>
learned, and worthy man; Made aboue fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeeres ſince in Germanie, After by tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueile a French creature, Now naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by mee into Engliſh like to his learned Author, to whom from my part moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſeruice is due. Surely at the firſt I meant not to haue ſet it abroad in Print, but my ſelfe onely to haue ſome certaintie to leane vnto, in a matter ſo full of controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and to yeeld a reaſon of my opinion. But ſince by my lending the Copie of mine owne hand to a friend, I am bereft thereof by ſome; And fearing leſt after my death it ſhould be Printed according to the humors of other, and wrong of the dead, who in his life approued my Tranſlation with his owne allowance: Therefore dreading, I ſay, wrong to him aboue any other reſpect, I haue by Anticipation preuented the worſt. J meant this to you, good daughter, for a New-yeeres gift, but altered by griefe for your Brothers broken arme. Farewell my
<pb facs="tcp:1338:3"/>
good ſweet <hi>Nanne.</hi> God bleſſe thee with the continuance of the comfort of his holy Spirit, that it may euer worke in you, and perſeuere with you to the ende, and in the ende.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>IN ANNAM FILIAM.</head>
            <l>Vt veniens Annus tibi plurima commodet ANNA,</l>
            <l>Voce pia Mater, ſupplice mente precor,</l>
            <l>Vt valeas, paritérque tuo cum Coniuge, Proles,</l>
            <l>Officijs iunctis, vita ſerena fluat.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>ELIZABETHA RVSSELLA, Dowager.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1338:4"/>
            <head>¶ A CERTAINE MAN wiſheth to all Chriſtians the health and peace of our Lord IESVS CHRIST.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE queſtion of the Supper of IESVS CHRIST,</hi> and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Thankeſgiuing, hath brought foorth to vs, aboue other things, a cruel and pernitious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. For the other Authors of ſects, <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and <hi>Suencfeldians,</hi> be neither lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nor of our family. But this is a ciuill and domesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call euill, a bloody and deadly wound hidden in our bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els. Surely it is a lamentable and horrible matter, that the thing which was first instituted for the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mens minds in loue, and concord, and fellowſhip of the body of Chriſt, which is the Church, is now wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to variance, and confuſion. And if there haue bene any good in this broile, it hath bene in the ſilence and ſorrow of good and learned men: of whom aſwell the miſliking ſheweth that there is ſomewhat in both parts that might be amended, and prayer and earneſt deſire may percaſe ſomewhat obtaine at Gods hand, that contention taken away, the agreement of minds may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine ioyne in one. But this booke which is made tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb facs="tcp:1338:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
this queſtion, whoſe ſoeuer it bee, ſure it ſeemeth to be the worke of a good, learned and modeſt man, and one that hath bene long, much, and well exerciſed in the Monuments of our Fathers and Elders. Neither doeth it moue mee, that he would not be named; for becauſe there is no bitter word in this disputation, and he doth reaſon of the matter learnedly, well, and truely, neither doth ſeeme willing to craue thankes at mens hands, nor to haue taken this Treatie in hand, either for deſire of praiſe or greedines of Honour, but to be mooued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by the common ſorrow and hurt, to make an entry to that thing, the which many men greatly deſiring the peace of Chriſts Church, haue wiſhed with earneſt and continuall prayers: namely, the remembrance of the Chriſtian peace, and the forgetting of deuiliſh debate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bucer,</hi> whom I with honour ſpeake of and for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance ſake, had found and made a way to this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and there was great agreement of minds betweene him and <hi>Luther:</hi> and hee pacified the Churches of the <hi>Heluetians,</hi> and while hee liued there was peace and quietneſſe: but when they were both dead, beholde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine bitter bookes on both ſides. And ſurely they be to be pardoned which write vnwillingly: but thoſe which without cauſe haue renued this wound, (if there be any ſuch) theſe ſurely ſeeme to me little to feare what men iudge of them, or to eſteeme the peace which Chriſt gaue and left vnto vs. But I returne to this Booke, which pleaſeth me beſt aboue other in this kinde of argument; not, that I will altogether allow it to the Congregation,
<pb facs="tcp:1338:5"/>
but becauſe it ſeemeth to come neereſt to the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of this contention. For which cauſe he that cannot inuent a better, if he be not content with this, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not defend his owne, let him take heed that hee doe not that for mans ſake, which he ought to leaue vndone for Chriſtes cauſe: namely, that he nouriſh not contention, which is the greateſt enemie the Church can haue. I ſee nothing concluded in this disputation, that either is repugnant from the nature of our Religion, or not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably ynough ſpoken of this ſo great &amp; ſinguler my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie; both which things if both the parts had retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or followed, we ſhould haue had quietneſſe long ere this. I blame neither part, I beare good will to both, I loue both. And if that were done in writing that is done, and that of many, with good conſcience in the leading of our life, and retaining and eſteeming the friends on both ſides, men ſhould both haue written and diſputed of this question on both ſides, with leſse offence and bitterneſse. But now wee write in ſuch ſort, as though wee did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the perſons, and not the cauſe, and apply the trueth of the cauſe, not to the ordinance of Chriſt, but to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of men. Ieſus Chriſt reſtore to vs his peace, which he gaue and left vnto vs when hee depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hence, which we haue lost by theſe our contentions: Ieſus Chriſt, I ſay, whoſe Victory, Triumph, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Praiſe, and Glory, be for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1338:5"/>
            <head>¶ A way of Reconciliation touching the trueth, nature and ſubſtance of the Body, or of the Fleſh and Blood of CHRIST in the <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat good man doeth not ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or what man zealous in Religion, doeth not often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile the pitifull and vnluckie contention about the LORDS SVPPER, which hath now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeres troubled the Churches of CHRIST which haue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the pure doctrine, whereby not onely brotherly Loue is broken, but alſo cities and whole countreys be thereby brought in danger? For whereas after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling the darkeneſſe of Ignorance, and the happy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring to the Church the gift of tongues, a certaine new Light was reſtored to the world, and the Goſpel had begun to take ſo great roote, that thereby hope of very great fruit was offered to enſue: By and by this ſharpe and vehement contention, burſting in among the chiefe champions of the Word, hath miſerably troubled theſe very good beginnings. For looke what weapons they had valiantly vſed, in ſetting foorth the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1338:6"/>
trueth, &amp; in ouerthrowing the enemies of the Goſpel, the very ſame, after this ſtrife was riſen, did they bend one againſt another. So that the happie courſe of the Goſpel that began to flouriſh is not only hindered, but alſo by factions &amp; diſcords, the matter is come to that paſſe, that vnleſſe the mighty Right-hand of the Lord do reſiſt, the trueth doeth ſeeme to appaule and decay againe, yea, and to returne to the former confuſion.</p>
            <p>For if we will iudge the matter truely, no force hath ſo much withſtand the inlarging of the Goſpel, no not the deceits and inchantments of the idole of <hi>Rome,</hi> not the crueltie of Princes againſt the flocke of CHRIST, not the troubleſome motions of breeders of Sects, as this onely raſh contention hath done hurt, which brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the minds of godly men ſorrow, to the enemies cauſe to reioyce, and to the weake and vnlearned, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and falling. And ſurely there is no doubt, but that our owne wickedneſſe hath bene the originall of this ſo great an euil, as it hath bene of many other: For wee not regarding, or rather contemning the light of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vs, are iuſtly thought vnworthy of ſo great a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit. Which thing alſo is the cauſe, that albeit many learned &amp; good men vnderſtand what profit it ſhould be for the Chriſtian common wealth ſpeedily to paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie this quarrell, and to ende the contentions, few not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding doe earneſtly traueile about this matter; And if any haue attempted it, it ſeemeth to fall out as vnluckily taken in hand to the contrary part. For my part, when I ſaw no end could be made of ſtrife, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hope in any one of better ſequele, I thought beſt to commit the matter to GOD by prayer, and with ſilence to looke for helpe in ſeaſon at his hands. Yet in this meane ſpace I thought it my part, not to neglect a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo great waight, but after examination had of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1338:6"/>
chiefe points of this controuerſie, to bolt out what was trueth, and what not; and then to determine vpon a ſure grounded opinion, both by authoritie of holy Scripture, and by the vndoubted teſtimonies of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, aſwell to ſatisfie my ſelfe, as to yeeld a reaſon thereof to any that ſhould perhaps demand it of mee: that the minde ſhould not wauer continually to &amp; fro, toſſed as it were with the contrary violence of winds.</p>
            <p>While I take this worke in hand, &amp; diligently tread the ſteps of the old Interpreters, me thinketh I perceiue (vnleſſe my opinion deceiue me) that this controuerſie is not ſo intangled, nor darke, as moſt men ſuppoſe, and that theſe ſharp co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentions haue come rather by mens fault, then by the nature of the matter; and that the way of Reconciliation ſhall not bee ſo hard with men, deſirous rather of the trueth then of quarrelling.</p>
            <p>Wherefore albeit I took in hand this worke, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be, priuately to my ſelfe, yet becauſe among my friends certaine good men and well giuen were ſo deſirous, I did not greatly paſſe to haue it come to the eares &amp; eyes of other, that if there be herein any profit, it may alſo do them good. The cauſe I haue thought good ſo to diuide, that briefly it may bee brought to three eſpecial points: Firſt wil I ſhew the trueth of the body of CHRIST in the Sacrament to be giuen to the faithful, and that theſe termes <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Subſtance</hi> are not to be ſhunned, but that they of old time diſputing of the Sacrament vſed them: Then will I declare the difference betweene the Lords proper body, and that which is in the Sacrament, and that the olde Fathers were of that opinion: And laſtly I will ſet foorth at large, what maner of Body that is which is receiued in the myſterie, &amp; why it is called by that name, after the opinion of the ſelfe ſame Fathers. Which things once
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1338:7"/>
expounded, a man may eaſily iudge of the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie. Firſt, it is manifeſt ynough by the declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Euangeliſts <hi>Matthew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. <hi>26.</hi> c. Matth. <hi>14.</hi> c. Luke <hi>22.</hi> c.</note> 
               <hi>Marke</hi> and <hi>Luke,</hi> that our Lord IESVS CHRIST, when he ſhould depart out of this world, and leauing the earth, ſhould goe vp to the Father, did ordeine the Sacrament of his Body and Blood in the preſence of his diſciples at Supper; and ſo when he had taken the bread, he bleſſed, brake it and gaue it to them, ſaying, <hi>This is my body:</hi> After the like maner the Cup alſo, ſaying, <hi>This Cup is the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament in my Blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Doe this in remembrance of me. Paul</hi> alſo writeth to the ſame effect to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle the 11. chapter, rehearſing in a maner the very ſame words,<note place="margin">Et cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> &amp; in the tenth chapter, <hi>The Cup</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of bleſsing which we bleſſe, is it not the partaking of the Blood of Christ? The bread which we breake, is it not the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of the Body of Chriſt?</hi> By theſe words of the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, and the Apoſtle, they of old time were of that opinion that CHRIST our Lord, which is Trueth it ſelfe, ſpake theſe things truly, and did in deed performe thoſe things that he ſpake, ſo that no place of doubt might any more be left, concerning the trueth of the matter.</p>
            <p>Moreouer thoſe words which in the ſixt chapter of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn <hi>6.</hi> c.</note> the Lord ſpake, <hi>My fleſh is meat indeed, and my blood is drinke indeed, &amp;c. The bread which I will giue you is my fleſh. And vnleſſe you eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man, and drinke his Blood, &amp;c.</hi> The Fathers with great accord, as well Grecians as Latines, doe apply to the <hi>Sacrament of Thankeſgiuing;</hi> And that they haue interpreted thoſe places ſo, both in <hi>Iohn,</hi> and the reſt of the Euangeliſts and <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the teſtimonies that follow taken out of the authors themſelues,<note place="margin">Iustin Martir Apol. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> ſhal happily proue.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> in his ſecond Apologie writeth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1338:7"/>
thus, <hi>And this meate is called with vs, that is, Thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, &amp;c.</hi> whereof none other may be partaker but he, which both beleeueth thoſe things to be true which we ſay, &amp; alſo hath bene purified with the waſhing, which is giuen for the remiſsion of ſinnes, and regeneration, and alſo ſo liueth as CHRIST hath appointed. For wee take not theſe things to be common and wonted bread, and accuſtomed drinke, but euen as the word of God IESVS CHRIST our Sauiour was made man, and had both fleſh and blood for our ſaluation: Euen ſo in like maner wee haue bene taught, that the meate which is hallowed by the prayers of the word that we receiued of him, and by which our blood and fleſh, by a change made are nouriſhed, is both the fleſh &amp; blood of the ſame CHRIST which was made man. For the Apoſtles in their Commentaries, which be called the Goſpels, haue left in writing, that CHRIST did ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them, and that he ſaid, when he had taken bread and giuen thankes, <hi>Doe this in remembrance of me, This is my body.</hi> And that when he had taken the cup and giuen thankes hee ſaid, <hi>This is my Blood.</hi> Partly the other words of this teſtimoniall doe affirme the trueth of his body: and chiefly becauſe by a ſimilitude taken of the two natures in CHRIST, he declareth that there be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo two natures in the Sacrament, namely of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſigne, and of the fleſh &amp; Blood of IESVS CHRIST.</p>
            <p>Alike vnto this is ſpoken in <hi>Irenaeus</hi> in his 4. booke: For how ſay they againe that the fleſh commeth into corruption, &amp; doth not receiue life which is nouriſhed of the body and Blood of the Lord? Therefore let them either change their opinion, or elſe abſtaine to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the things which are aforeſaid: but our opinion is agreeing to the Sacrament of thankeſgiuing, and this Sacrament againe confirmeth our opinion: For wee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1338:8"/>
offer thoſe things that be his, preaching agreeably the partaking and trueth of Fleſh and Spirit. For euen as the bread which is of the earth receiuing the calling vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, is now no more common bread, but a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thankſgiuing, made of two things, earthly and Heauenly: ſo alſo our bodies receiuing the Sacrament of thankeſgiuing, be not now corruptible, becauſe they haue the hope of reſurrection. The ſame man in his fift booke; and becauſe wee be his members, and are nouriſhed by the creature, &amp; he giueth vs the creature, making his Sonne to ariſe, and raining as he liſteth, the ſame Cup which is a creature, he confirmed to be his Body, by which he increaſeth our bodies. When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both the Cup mixed, and the bread made, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the word of God, it is made the Sacrament of the blood and body of CHRIST, whereof both the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of our fleſh is increaſed, &amp; conſiſteth: how then doeth he denie, that the fleſh is able to receiue the gift of God which is life Euerlaſting, ſeeing it is nouriſhed with the blood and bodie of CHRIST?</p>
            <p>Theſe words of <hi>Irenaeus</hi> albeit not very dark, yet wil they be more plaine if we adde certaine things to them out of <hi>S. Auguſtine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">August. tit. de conſecrat. dist. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> He in his booke of the <hi>Sentences</hi> of <hi>Proſperus,</hi> and is found <hi>De conſecratione distinct. 2.</hi> writeth thus, This is it that we ſay, and that by al meanes we la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to proue, that the Sacrifice of the Church is made two maner awayes, that it conſiſteth of two things, Of the viſible forme of Sacraments, and the inuiſible fleſh and blood of our Lord IESVS CHRIST: of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and of the ſubſtance of the Sacrament, that is the body of CHRIST. As the perſon of CHRIST con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of God and man, ſince CHRIST himſelfe is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry God and very man, becauſe euery thing conteineth in it ſelfe the nature and trueth of thoſe things whereof
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1338:8"/>
it is made; But the ſacrifice of the Church is made of two things, of the Sacrament, and of the ſubſtance of the Sacrament, that is, the body of CHRIST. There is therefore the Sacrament, and the ſubſtance of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament the bodie of CHRIST. <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> repeateth that compariſon between the perſon of CHRIST, and the Sacrament of thankeſgiuing, and therein hee ſaith plainely, that the trueth and nature of the bodie is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined. The ſame man <hi>De conſecrat. distinct. 2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this myſticall Sacrament of the Cup made in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure or in trueth? The trueth ſaith, <hi>My fleſh is verily meat, and my blood is verily drinke;</hi> Elſe how can it bee a great matter, <hi>The bread that I ſhall giue, is my fleſh for the life of the world,</hi> vnleſſe it bee very fleſh? But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not godly that CHRIST ſhould be deuoured with teeth, the Lords will was to haue this bread and wine in myſterie to be by his power made his fleſh and blood, in veritie by the conſecration of the holy Ghoſt, and to be daily offered myſticallie for the life of the world. That like as his true fleſh is created of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin by the holy Ghoſt without the companie of man, ſo by this ſame Spirit the ſame bodie myſtically, is conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated of the ſubſtance of bread and wine. The body of CHRIST is both trueth and figure; Trueth, in that the bodie and blood of CHRIST by the power of the holy Ghoſt, is made by the ſtrength thereof of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of bread and wine: And the figure is that which outwardly is perceiued.</p>
            <p>The ſame man in the ſame title:<note place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note> They that eate and drinke CHRIST, eate and drinke life. To eate him is to be refreſhed; to drinke him is to liue. That which is viſiblie taken in the Sacrament, is eaten and drunke ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually in very trueth.<note place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note> The ſame man in his booke of the <hi>Sentences</hi> of <hi>Proſperus</hi> in the ſame title ſaith: But we
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1338:9"/>
in the forme of bread and wine, which we ſee, do honor inuiſible things, namely, fleſh and blood. Neither doe we alike take theſe two formes, as we did take them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the conſecration, ſeeing that we faithfully confeſſe that before the conſecration, they be bread and wine which nature hath framed, but after the conſecration, they be the fleſh &amp; blood of CHRIST which the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing hath hallowed. He againe vpon the 54. Pſalme, Vntill the world come to an end the Lord is aboue, yet for all that the Lords trueth is alſo here with vs: For it is fit that the body in the which he roſe againe, ſhould be in one place, but his trueth is ſpred euery where. He alſo in his Epiſtle to <hi>Irenaeus:</hi> CHRIST is bread of the which hee who ſo eateth, liueth for euer; whereof hee himſelfe ſaith thus, <hi>And the bread which I will giue is my fleſh for the life of the world.</hi> And he expoundeth it how it is bread, not onely according to the word whereby all things liue, but according to the fleſh that hee tooke for the life of the world. For mans fleſh which was dead through ſinne being knit to pure fleſh incorporat, made one with it, doth liue by his ſpirit euen as one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die by his owne ſpirit: But he that is not of the body of CHRIST, liueth not of the Spirit of CHRIST. Hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath plainly inough proued the trueth and nature of the body of CHRIST in this Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hilar. de tri. lib. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Hilarie</hi> in his 8. booke of the <hi>Trinitie:</hi> I would know now of them that alledge vnitie of wil between the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Sonne, whether CHRIST nowadayes be in vs by trueth of nature, or by agreement of will. For if the Word be verily made fleſh, and wee receiue the word, verily fleſh in the Lords meate: how ſhould a man not ſuppoſe him to remaine naturally in vs, which being borne man, tooke to himſelfe an vnſeparable na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, now of our fleſh, and hath mixed the nature of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1338:9"/>
owne fleſh with the nature of eternitie vnder the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his fleſh to be partaked among vs? And a little after: Therefore whoſoeuer wil denie the Father to be naturally in CHRIST, let him firſt denie either him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be naturally in CHRIST, or CHRIST to be in him, becauſe the Father in CHRIST, and CHRIST in vs, do make vs to be one thing in them. If CHRIST therefore did verily take the fleſh of our bodie, &amp; if the ſame man which was borne of the Virgine <hi>Mary</hi> be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily CHRIST; and we verily take vnder a myſterie the fleſh of his body, and thereby ſhal become one, becauſe the Father is in him, and hee in vs: How is the vnitie of will alledged, ſeeing the naturall propertie (by meanes of the Sacrament,) is a Sacrament of perfect vnitie? Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a little after; For thoſe things which wee ſpeake of the naturall trueth of CHRIST in vs, vnleſſe we learne of him, we ſpeake fooliſhly and wickedly. For he ſaith, <hi>My fleſh is meat in deed, and my Blood is drinke in deed: Hee that eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood, remaineth in mee, and I in him.</hi> There is no place left of doubting of the trueth of Fleſh and Blood: For now it is verily Fleſh, and verily Blood, both by the confeſsion of our Lord himſelfe, and alſo by our Faith; and theſe things being receiued by eating and drinking, doe worke that effect, that both wee be in CHRIST, and CHRIST is in vs. Is not this trueth? Let it happen vnto them not to bee true, which denie IESVS CHRIST to be very God. And ſoone after: And ſo by a Mediator, the perfit Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhould be taught, when as wee abiding in him hee ſhould abide in the Father, and he abiding in the Father ſhould abide in vs, and ſo ſhould we clime to the vnitie of the Father, when hee is naturally according to his birth in him, we alſo ſhould be naturally in him, ſo long as he abideth naturally in vs. And that this natural vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1338:10"/>
is in vs, he hath thus witneſſed, <hi>He that eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood, abideth in me and I in him.</hi> And by and by he addeth, This is truely the cauſe of our life: for that we haue CHRIST remaining in vs carnal men according to the fleſh, whereas wee ſhall liue hereafter by him, after the ſame ſort as he liueth by the Father. If we therefore liue naturally by him after the fleſh, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hauing taken vpon vs the nature of his fleſh, how hath he not the Father after the ſpirit naturally in him, ſince he liueth by the Father? And he concludeth: To this end be theſe things rehearſed by vs, becauſe the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiks affirming falſly the vnitie of wil onely betweene the Father and the Sonne, vſed for the example of our vnitie with the Lord, as though we were vnited to the Sonne, and by the Sonne to the Father, only by obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and will of Religion, and no propertie of naturall fellowſhip were granted to vs by the Sacrament of his fleſh and blood: whereas in deed the myſterie of the true and naturall vnitie ſhould be taught, both for the honour of the Sonne of God that is giuen vs, and for the Sonne carnally abiding in vs, and wee knit corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and vnſeparably in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hilarius</hi> doeth manifeſtly teach the true and naturall partaking of the fleſh of CHRIST in the Sacrament; And as plainely doeth <hi>Cyrillus</hi> witneſſe the ſame in the 10.<note place="margin">Cyrillus lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> booke chap. 13. when he ſaith, Yet wee denie not that wee be ioyned ſpiritually in CHRIST by a right faith, and ſincere loue: but that wee haue no maner of ioyning with him according to the fleſh, that truely we vtterly denie. And ſoone after; But doth hee happily thinke that the vertue of the myſticall bleſsing is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to vs? which when it is wrought in vs, doth it not alſo make CHRIST to dwell corporally in vs, by the partaking of the fleſh of CHRIST? For why be the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1338:10"/>
members of the faithfull the members of CHRIST? <hi>Know ye not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that your members be the members of Chriſt? Shal I therefore make the members of Chriſt the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of an harlot?</hi> Our Sauiour alſo ſaith, <hi>He that eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood, remaineth in me and I in him;</hi> whereby it ought to be conſidered, that CHRIST is in vs, not onely by that accuſtomed qualitie which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by loue, but alſo further by a naturall partaking. For euen as if a man ſhall melt waxe by the fire, and mingle it with other waxe which is likewiſe melted, ſo that one lumpe may ſeeme to be made of both; So by the communion of the body and blood of CHRIST he is in vs, and wee in him. For this corruptible nature of the bodie could not otherwiſe be brought to vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and life, vnleſſe the body of naturall life ſhould be ioyned thereto. The ſame man alſo in his 4.<note place="margin">Idem in Io. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> booke vpon <hi>Iohn</hi> the 14. chapter doeth witneſſe: For truely it behoueth that not onely the ſoule ſhould aſcend into bleſſed life by the holy Ghoſt, but alſo that this rude and earthly body ſhould be brought againe to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie, by a taſte, feeling, and meate like vnto it. The ſame man in his 11. book vpon <hi>Iohn cap. 27.</hi> The Sonne,<note place="margin">Idem in Io. lib. <hi>11.</hi> cap. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> as man, is made one with vs corporally by the myſtical bleſsings, but ſpiritually as God. And a little after; For we receiuing corporally and ſubſtantially, (as it hath bene ſaid) the Sonne of God which is made one by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with the Father, be made pure and glorified, being partakers of the nature that is from aboue. The ſame man in the ſame book vpon the 26. chapter:<note place="margin">Idem eodem lib. cap. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> For to the end therefore ye might knit euery one of vs among our ſelues and God, although wee differ both in body and ſoule, yet hath he found a meane agreeable to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of his Father, and his owne wiſdome. For he bleſsing with his owne body (through the myſtical
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1338:11"/>
communion) them that beleeue, doth make vs one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, both with himſelfe, and alſo among our ſelues. For who wil thinke thoſe diſtant from this naturall vnion, which be vnited in one CHRIST by the vnion of one CHRISTS bodie? <hi>For if all we eat one bread, we be made all one body.</hi> And within few wordes after: But that this bodily vniting to CHRIST is attained by the parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his fleſh, <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe againe doeth witneſſe, diſputing of the myſterie of godlineſſe: <hi>the which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath not bene knowen to the ſonnes of men in other gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, as it hath bene reueiled now to his holy Apoſtles and Prophets in the Spirit, that the Gentiles be coheires and ioyned in body, and equall partakers of the promiſe in Chriſt.</hi> The ſame man to <hi>Caloſyrius:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem ad Calo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrium.</note> For that wee ſhould not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide of the fleſh and blood ſet vpon the holy Altars, God ſubmitting himſelfe to our frailtie, putteth a force of life into thoſe things that bee offered, turning them into the trueth of his owne fleſh, that the body of life as it were a certaine quickning ſeed, may bee found in vs: whereupon he addeth, <hi>Doe this in a remembrance of me.</hi> Hitherto <hi>Cyrillus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cyprianus de coena Domini.</note>
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> of the Supper of the Lord; This bread not in outward apparence, but in nature changed by the mightie power of the Word, is made fleſh, which the Lord did reach to his diſciples. And in the ſame place; Who euen to this day createth, and ſanctifieth, &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and diuideth, to thoſe that take it godly, this his moſt true and holy bodie.<note place="margin">Hieron. in Matth. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrat. dist. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hierom</hi> vpon <hi>Matthew, De conſecrat. diſt. 2.</hi> He tooke bread, which is the comforter of man, and paſſed to the true Sacrament of Paſſeouer. That as <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> for a figure therof before had done when he offered bread and wine, he ſhould repreſent it in the trueth of his bodie and blood.<note place="margin">Chryſost. in Io. Hom. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> vpon <hi>Iohn, Hom. 45.</hi> But that not onely by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1338:11"/>
loue, but euen in very deed wee ſhould be turned into that fleſh, he worketh the ſame by the meate which hee hath giuen vs. For when he ment to bring his loue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, he ioyned himſelfe to vs by his body, and made himſelfe one with vs, that the body might be knit with the head. The ſame man <hi>Homil. 61.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem Hom. <hi>61.</hi>
               </note> Therefore that we ſhould be this not only by charitie, but in very deed ſhould bee mingled with that fleſh, this is brought to paſſe by the meat which hee hath giuen vs. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> hath alſo many other ſayings to the ſame meaning.</p>
            <p>Thoſe things that <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> writeth in his 6.<note place="margin">Ambroſ. lib. <hi>6.</hi> de ſacra. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> booke the firſt chapter of the Sacraments, do agree with theſe: Euen as our Lord IESVS CHRIST is the true Sonne of God, not as men be by grace, but as a Sonne of the ſubſtance of the Father; ſo is that which wee take, the very fleſh of CHRIST, and they drinke his very blood as he himſelfe ſaid. And a little after; Then when his diſciples could not away with the talke of CHRIST, but hearing that he would giue them his fleſh to eate, and his blood to drinke, they went away: But <hi>Peter</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſaid, <hi>Thou hast the words of eternall life, and whither ſhould I goe from thee?</hi> Leſt therefore any moe ſhould ſay this, as though there ſhould be a kinde of lothſomneſſe of blood, but that the grace of redemption might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, therefore receiueſt thou the Sacrament in a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, but thou obteineſt the grace and vertue of the true nature. The ſame man in his 4. booke the 4.<note place="margin">Idem lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> cap. Thou ſeeſt therefore how effectuall in operation the word of CHRIST is. If then there be ſo great effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in the word of our Lord IESVS CHRIST, that that ſhould begin to bee, which was not; How much more is it of effect, to make thoſe things to be that were before, and to be changed into another thing? And ſo that which was bread before the conſecration, the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1338:12"/>
ſame is become the body of CHRIST after the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, becauſe the word of CHRIST doeth change the creature; And ſo of bread is made the body of CHRIST, and the wine mixed with water in the cup, is made blood by the conſecration of the heauenly word. But perhaps thou wilt ſay, I ſee not the forme of blood, But it hath a likeneſſe. For euen as thou haſt taken the likenes of his death, ſo alſo doeſt thou drinke the ſimilitude of his blood, that there ſhould be no ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring of blood, and yet the price of our redemption wrought. Alſo before the wordes of CHRIST the cup is full of wine &amp; water: after the words of CHRIST haue wrought, there is the blood made which hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed the people. Therefore marke how the word of CHRIST is able to make alteration in all things. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, CHRIST himſelfe doeth teſtifie, that wee doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue his bodie and blood, of whoſe fulneſſe and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie we ought not to doubt. Likewiſe peraduenture thou ſaieſt, I ſee another thing, How proueſt thou that I do receiue the bodie of CHRIST? This remaineth yet for vs to proue, that this is not it which nature hath faſhioned, but it, that bleſsing hath hallowed; and that there is greater force of the bleſsing, then of nature: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nature it ſelfe is alſo changed by the bleſsing. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: But if the bleſsing of man was of ſuch force that it could turne nature; What doe we ſay of the very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly conſecration, whereas the very wordes of the Lord our Sauiour do worke? For this Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which thou receiueſt, is wrought by the words of CHRIST. But if the word of <hi>Elias</hi> was of ſuch force that it could bring fire from heauen; Shall not the word of CHRIST be of power to change the kinds of elements?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Euſebius Emyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenus de conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. dist. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Euſebius Emyſſenus</hi> likewiſe, who was in yeeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> doth witnes in theſe wordes, the opinion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1338:12"/>
which was then had of the Sacrament, and it is had <hi>De conſecrat. dist. 2.</hi> Whereupon the heauenly authoritie confirmeth, <hi>That my fleſh is verily meat, and my blood is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily drinke.</hi> Let therefore all doubt of misbeliefe be laid aſide, becauſe hee that is author of the gift is likewiſe witneſſe of the trueth. For the inuiſible prieſt doeth turne with his word, by a ſecret power, the viſible crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures into the ſubſtance of his bodie and blood, ſaying thus, <hi>Take ye, eate ye, this is my body,</hi> and the hallowing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing repeated, <hi>Take ye, drinke ye, this is my blood.</hi> Therefore euen as the height of the heauens, the depth of waters, and largeneſſe of earth had their being of nothing, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly at the becke of the Lord that commanded: ſo with the like power in the ſpirituall Sacraments when power commandeth, effect obeieth. How great there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and wonderfull benefits the force of the heauenly bleſsing doeth worke. How it ought not to ſeeme a new &amp; vnpoſsible matter to thee, that earthly and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal things bee turned into the ſubſtance of Chriſt, aske thy ſelfe that art borne anew in Chriſt. Hee againe in his oration of the bodie of the Lord: Let not man dout but that the chiefe creatures at the becke of power by the preſence of Maieſtie, may be turned into the nature of the Lords bodie.<note place="margin">Leo &amp; Syn. Rom. de conſec. dist. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Leo</hi> the biſhop and the Synode of <hi>Rome</hi> as is there declared; In what darkneſſe of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, in what bodie of ſlouthfulnes haue they hitherto lyen, that they would neither learne by hearing, nor know by reading that which is ſo agreeable in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation vvith the confeſsion of all perſons, that the trueth of the bodie and blood of Chriſt, among the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of the communion cannot be kept in ſilence, no not of the tongues of Infants, becauſe in that myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call diſtribution of the ſpirituall food, this is giuen, and this is receiued, that wee receiuing the ſtrength of this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1338:13"/>
heauenly meat, doe become his fleſh, which was made our fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gregor. hom. Paſch. ibidem.</note>
               <hi>Gregorie homilia paſchali,</hi> and it is there rehearſed. For he is daily eaten and drunke in trueth, but yet he remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vvhole and one, and vnſpotted. And it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a great myſterie, and to be reuerenced with feare, becauſe there is one thing to the ſight, and another to the vnderſtanding.<note place="margin">Euthym. in Matth. cap. <hi>64.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Euthymius</hi> vpon <hi>Matthew cap. 64.</hi> Therfore euen as the old Teſtament had ſacrifices and blood, ſo alſo hath the Nevv, namely the bodie and blood of the Lord. For hee ſaid not, Theſe be ſignes of my body, but he ſaid, <hi>Theſe be my body &amp; my blood</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vvee muſt not take heed to the nature of thoſe things that bee ſet before vs, but to the vertue of them. For euen as aboue nature hee did deifie the fleſh that vvas taken of the Virgine (if it bee lavvfull to vſe this phraſe) ſo alſo doeth hee vnſpeakeably change theſe things into his very liuely bodie, and into his very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood, and into the grace of them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Theophil. in Matth. cap. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Theophilactus</hi> vpon <hi>Matt. 26.</hi> In ſaying <hi>This is my body,</hi> hee declareth that the bread vvhich is ſanctified vpon the Altar, is the very body of the Lord, and not a figure anſvvering vnto it; for he ſaid not, This is a figure, but <hi>This is my body.</hi> The bread is transformed by an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable working into the body of Chriſt; albeit it ſeemes bread to vs that bee weake, and abhorre to eate raw fleſh, eſpecially the fleſh of man. For that cauſe tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread appeareth, but it is fleſh. The ſame man vpon <hi>Marke cap. 14.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem in Marc. cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> When he had bleſſed it, that is, vvhen he had giuen thanks, he brake the bread, which thing alſo we do, adding thereto prayers, <hi>This is my body:</hi> this I ſay which you take. For the bread is not a figure and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample onely of the Lords body, but it is turned into the very bodie of Chriſt. <hi>Damaſcenus</hi> doth alſo vvrite al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1338:13"/>
the very ſame things <hi>lib. 4. cap. 14.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Damaſ. de fide. Orth. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> The bread and vvine is not a figure of the body and blood of Chriſt to the right faith; for God forbid wee ſhould beleeue ſo: but it is the very deified bodie of the Lord by his owne ſaying, <hi>This is my body;</hi> not a figure of my bodie, but my bodie, <hi>This is my blood,</hi> not a figure of my blood.</p>
            <p>Many other places alſo may be brought forth here, taken out of the Fathers, vvhich agree with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, by al the vvhich vve may eaſily perceiue, what vvas the opinion of them al, aſmuch as apperteineth to this part of our diuiſion, namely, that the Sacrament of Thankeſgiuing is not only a figure of the Lords body, but alſo comprehendeth in it the trueth, nature &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the ſame. For it cannot be a doubt to any man that will read their writings, that they oftentimes vſed theſe termes, Truly, Naturally, &amp; Subſtantially, &amp; the coniugates of them. And although our faith dependeth not vpon men, but vpon the word of God: yet ſince they defend their opinion with the authoritie of the Scripture, it is very profitable for godly minds &amp; deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of the trueth, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider how ſo many notable men both for godlineſſe and learning, haue vnderſtood the words of the Scripture, and with great agreement left their interpretations to their ſucceſsion; neither ſhall he auoid the blame of raſhneſſe (whoſoeuer he be) that dare deſpiſe ſo great authoritie.</p>
            <p>Now let vs take in hand our ſecond part. Whether they of ancient time haue thought that there is any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the body of our Lord, which is diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted in the Sacrament, and that which was taken of the Virgin mother, vvhich aſcended into heauen, and from thence ſhall come at his time to Iudgement. That is, whether the body of Chriſt bee in the Sacrament of Thankeſgiuing, according to the proper ſignification
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1338:14"/>
of a mans body, or otherwiſe, differing ſomewhat from a proper body. When I ſpeake of a proper body, I meane a body properly vnderſtand, which ſhall ſuffice to haue once admoniſhed. Then vvhether theſe termes, Trueth, Nature, Subſtance ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand after the common ſort in this matter, or after a more peculiar maner, and more fit for the Sacraments.</p>
            <p>Finally, whether there be any aequiuocation in theſe termes or no. For there is not onely heed to bee taken with vvhat words the fathers haue ſpoken in old time, but alſo what they ment when they ſo ſpake. And that is not to be proued by our ovvne or other mens inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or light coniectures, but by the aſſured teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Fathers themſelues. But that wee may haue the eaſier entrie to this matter, wee muſt perceiue that the body of Chriſt is called not after one maner vviſe in the Scriptures, but ſundry vvaies. Firſt, as that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die as vvas taken vpon him, and borne of the Virgin, vvhich alſo roſe againe, and aſcended into heauen, of the vvhich this vvas ſpoken, <hi>Mee truely ſhall ye not haue alway.</hi> And this, <hi>I leaue the world, and go to my Father</hi> And this, <hi>Feele and behold, for a ſpirit hath not fleſh and bones, as you ſee me haue.</hi> Secondarily, as the Church is called the body of Chriſt, according to this ſaying, <hi>You are Chriſts body.</hi> And this, <hi>And he gaue him to be a head ouer all things to the Church which is his body.</hi> Thirdly, as the Sacrament of the body of Chriſt is called the body of Chriſt, wherof Chriſt himſelfe ſaid, <hi>This is my body.</hi> And <hi>Paul, The bread which we breake, is it not the partaking of the body of Christ?</hi> And this, <hi>Making no difference of the Lords bodie.</hi> Which places be vnderſtood of the Sacrament of his body, vvhereby it commeth to paſſe, that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſt is called properly and vnproperly. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly that bodie taken of the Virgin; Vnproperly, the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1338:14"/>
Sacrament and the Church. That the Church is not properly the bodie of Chriſt, no man doubteth. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth that vvee prooue the ſame of the Sacrament. This is eſpecially to bee marked, as oft as they of old time treat of the Sacrament, they all apply to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament the vvords of our Lord, vvhich are ſpoken in the ſixt chapter of <hi>Iohn, My fleſh is verily meat, &amp; my blood is verily drinke. The bread which I will giue is my fleſh, and vnleſſe you eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man,</hi> &amp;c. Which things ſhalbe proued by their ovvne ſayings before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, and alſo by thoſe that ſhall follovv. Neither are they to bee allovved, that deny this chapter of <hi>Iohn</hi> to be referred to this Sacrament, ſeeing ſo great a troupe of vvitneſſes be againſt them. But the opinion of them ſeemed more probable, vvho as they iudge this Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt to ſet forth the humanitie of Chriſt leſſe then the reſt, and his diuinitie more amply: ſo doe declare that theſe things vvhich are rehearſed by the other Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts concerning the inſtitution, and outvvard cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of this Sacrament, are not at all mentioned of <hi>Iohn;</hi> but that he openeth &amp; expoundeth more plainly vnto vs the true and right vnderſtanding of them. And it is plaine that the mindes of the <hi>Capernaites</hi> vvhen the Lord ſaid, <hi>My fleſh is verily meat; And vnleſse ye eat the fleſh of the Sonne of man,</hi> &amp;c. vvere much offended and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and therefore leauing him departed, for they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood him too groſly, and after the common ſort. But his Tvvelue Apoſtles that taried by him being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed, and lift vp to a more higher meaning, and of more Maieſtie, heard of him, <hi>The words which I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken be ſpirit and life.</hi> Vpon this it commeth to paſſe, that all the old vvriters do flie the common iudgement and vſuall vnderſtanding in thoſe vvordes, <hi>This is my body,</hi> and vvhich the Lord ſpake of eating his fleſh, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1338:15"/>
a more diuine vvay of vnderſtanding them, and more agreeable to the Sacraments, as they themſelues affirme.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Chryſost. in Matth. cap. <hi>26.</hi> Hom. <hi>83.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> vpon <hi>Matthew 26. hom. 83.</hi> expounding the vvords of the Supper, <hi>Take ye, eate ye, this is my body,</hi> &amp;c. doth aske this queſtion, Why were they not troubled vvhen they heard this? And he anſvvereth, Becauſe he had taught them alreadie many and great things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this point before: Wherefore alſo hee did not confirme that vvhich they had often before perceiued. And not long after hee addeth, Hee himſelfe did alſo drinke of it, leaſt at the hearing of thoſe vvordes, they ſhould ſay, What? do vve then drinke blood, and eate fleſh? and vpon that might be troubled; For at the firſt alſo when he ſpake of theſe matters, many vvere offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded onely for the wordes. Leſt therefore this ſhould then alſo haue happened, he did this firſt himſelfe, that hee might bring them to the partaking of theſe myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries vvith a quiet minde. We be taught here by <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom,</hi> that the Apoſtles were not troubled when they heard the Lord ſay, <hi>Take ye, eat ye, this is my body;</hi> Becauſe they had bene alreadie taught before, hovv that which vvas ſpoken ought to be vnderſtood, namely where o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were offended, as it is in <hi>Iohn,</hi> &amp; ſaid, <hi>This is a hard ſaying,</hi> they abode and had learned, <hi>It is the Spirit that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth life, the fleſh profiteth nothing; The wordes that I haue ſpoken vnto you, are ſpirit &amp; life:</hi> that is to ſay, as the ſame <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in the ſame place expounded it, they are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually to bee vnderſtood: which ſelfe thing the Lord himſelfe confirmeth by his owne deed, vvhen hee did eat the ſame bread, &amp; drinke the vvine vvith them, leſt they ſhould thinke vpon any baſe or common matter, but ſhould be brought to the partaking of the myſteries with quiet minds. It is no hard matter to perceiue by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1338:15"/>
this that <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> vvriteth in this place, that it is one way a body, that Chriſt himſelfe called his body when he ſaid, <hi>Take ye, eat ye, this is my body,</hi> the which he alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth himſelfe together with his diſciples; and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vvay to bee his proper body which was fed vvith the other. The one did eat, the other was eaten, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a diuers ſort either of them is called his body.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe maketh alſo that vvhich <hi>Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus</hi> ſchoolemaſter to <hi>Origen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clemens Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and. lib. inſcrip. Paedagogus.</note> teacheth in his booke, intituled <hi>Paedagogus,</hi> when he ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The blood of Chriſt is two maner of wayes: the one fleſhie where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by vve are vvaſhed, the other ſpirituall vvherevvith we haue bene anointed.<note place="margin">Hierom. in Epi. ad Epheſ. ca. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Whom <hi>Hierom</hi> follovving vpon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> the firſt chapter ſaith, The blood and fleſh of Chriſt (ſaith he) is vnderſtood tvvo maner of vvayes: that is, either that ſpirituall and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, whereof he himſelfe ſpake, <hi>My fleſh is verily meat, and my blood is verily drinke; And vnleſse you eate my fleſh and drinke my blood, you ſhall not haue euerlaſting life:</hi> Or elſe the fleſh and blood that vvas crucified, that was ſhed vvith the ſpeare of the ſouldier. There bee tvvo things that <hi>Hierom</hi> teacheth in this place, That thoſe vvords in the <hi>6.</hi> chap. of <hi>Iohn,</hi> do appertaine to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, euen as <hi>Chryſostom</hi> doth: and that the fleſh that vvas crucified, doeth differ from that vvhich is in the Sacrament, vvhich he calleth Spirituall &amp; Diuine. The ſame man vpon <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> and is to be ſeen <hi>De conſecrat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem. in Leuit. de conſecrat. dist. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>dist. 2.</hi> Of this ſacrifice vvhich is by miracle vvrought for the remembrance of Chriſt it is lavvfull to eate: but of that which Chriſt offered vpon the Altar of the Croſſe, it is of it ſelf lavvful for no man to eat. A plaine and manifeſt diſtinction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtin in lib. ſenten. Proſperi.</hi>
               <note place="margin">August. in lib. Sent. Proſperi.</note> It is his fleſh vvhich co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1338:16"/>
with the forme of bread, we receiue in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and his blood which vnder the forme and taſt of wine we drinke, that is to ſay, the fleſh is the ſacrament of fleſh, and blood is the ſacrament of blood. By fleſh and blood being both inuiſible, ſpirituall, intelligible, is betokened the viſible &amp; ſenſible body of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, full of the grace of all vertues &amp; diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie. Who ſeeth not hovv plainly <hi>Auguſtine</hi> putteth a difference between the proper body of Chriſt which he termeth viſible and ſenſible, and that fleſh which we receiue in the ſacrament, vvhich he affirmeth to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible, ſpirituall, intelligible, and a ſigne of the other body?<note place="margin">Idem in Epist. ad Iren.</note> The ſame man in his Epiſtle to <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> You ſhall not eat this body which you ſee, and drinke that blood which they that ſhall crucifie me ſhall ſhed. The ſame truely, and not the ſame; The ſame inuiſiblie, and not the ſame viſibly. He putteth a difference when hee ſaith, Not this body: and againe, The ſame, &amp; not the ſame. The maner of the difference is, the ſame inuiſibly which hee termeth before the inuiſible body, namely the Sacrament of the body: and not the ſame viſibly, or the viſible body, which is referred to the proper body: for this body whereſoeuer it be, is viſible. The ſame man in his booke <hi>Sent. Proſperi:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem in lib. Sent. Proſperi.</note> Chriſt was once offered in himſelfe, yet is hee daily offered in the Sacrament, which is thus to be vnderſtood. That, in the outward ſhewing foorth of his body, in the diſtinction of all his members, very God, and very man, did but once hang vpon the Croſſe, offering himſelfe a liuely ſacrifice to the Father. The body which is in the Sacrament, hath neither outward ſhewing forth of the body, nor diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of members, but his proper body neuer wanteth his diſtinction of members.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Idem in Pſ. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note>The ſame man vpon the 33. Pſalme: And he was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1338:16"/>
in his owne hands. But my brethren, who can vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how this might be done in a man? For who can be caried in his owne hands? A man may well be caried in other mens hands, in his owne hands no man is caried. How it may be vnderſtond in <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe, according to the letter, we ſhall not finde, but in Chriſt wee ſhall finde it. For Chriſt was caried in his owne hands when he commending his owne body, ſaid, <hi>This is my body;</hi> for that body was caried in his hands, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward expounding himſelfe better he ſaith, And hee was caried in his own hands. How was he caried in his owne hands? Becauſe when he ment to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend that body and blood of his, hee tooke into his hands, that which the faithfull knew, and he caried himſelfe after a ſort, when he ſaid, <hi>This is my body.</hi> In ſaying that body was caried in his hands, and he tooke into his handes that which the faithfull knew, and he bare himſelfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort; he doeth declare that this ſaying is not to be vnderſtand ſimply of one ſelfe body, but that body that did carie was one, namely his proper bodie, and that which was caried another, to ſay, the Sacrament of his body.</p>
            <p>The ſame man vpon the 98. Pſalme,<note place="margin">Idem in Pſal. <hi>98.</hi>
               </note> It ſeemed a hard ſaying to them, when he ſaid, <hi>Vnleſſe a man do eate my fleſh, hee ſhall neuer haue euerlaſting life.</hi> They tooke it fooliſhly, imagined of it fleſhly, and thought that the Lord would haue cut certaine pieces out of his bodie to giue them, and they ſaid, <hi>This is a hard ſaying.</hi> They themſelues were hard, not the ſaying: for if they had not bene hard, but humble ſpirited, they would haue ſaid within themſelues; He ſpeaketh not this without a cauſe, there is may hap a certaine hid Sacrament in it; They would haue taried with him meeke ſpirited, not hardned, and haue learned of him that which thoſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1338:17"/>
that remained did learne when they were gone. For when his Twelue diſciples abode with him after their departure, they ſeemed to bewaile to him the death of them, becauſe they were offended at his wordes, and gone backe. But he inſtructed them &amp; ſaid vnto them, <hi>It is the Spirit that quickeneth, for the fleſh profiteth nothing; The words that I haue ſpoken to you, are Spirit and life,</hi> Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand you that ſpiritually which I haue ſpoken to you. You ſhall not eate this bodie which you ſee, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall you drinke the blood which they ſhall ſhed that crucifie me. I haue commended to you a certaine Sacrament. If it be ſpiritually vnderſtood, it will giue you life. Although of neceſsitie it muſt be miniſtred vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiblie, yet muſt it bee vnuiſibly vnderſtood, where hee ſaith, Not this bodie which you ſee, &amp;c. And I haue commended a certaine Sacrament vnto you; hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a plaine diſtinction betweene the two bodies, whereof one is properly his body, the other the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his body.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Idem de doct. Christ. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>The ſame man, <hi>De doctrina Chriſtiana lib 3. Vnleſſe you eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man and drinke his blood, yee ſhall haue no life in you.</hi> Hee ſeemeth to command a hainous and wicked thing; therefore it is a figure commanding that wee muſt communicate with the paſsion of the Lord, &amp; ſweetly and profitably lay vp in remembrance that his fleſh was crucified and wounded for vs. If we following the letter do vnderſtand it, as the words doe properly ſound, Hee ſeemeth (ſaith he) to command a hainous thing: therefore (hee ſaith) it is a figuratiue ſpeach, and ought not to be vnderſtood of the eating of his proper body, but of the Sacrament of his body, which is after a ſpirituall ſort the body of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Idem ad Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac. Epist. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note>The ſame man to <hi>Boniface</hi> in the 23. Epiſtle; For ſo wee ſpeake, as when Eaſter draweth nie, wee ſay, To
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1338:17"/>
morrow, or the day after is the paſsion of Chriſt, whereas indeed he ſuffered ſo many yeeres before, and that paſsion hath not at all bene made but once. For vpon very Eaſter day we ſay, This day the Lord roſe againe. whereas ſo many yeres are paſt ſince he roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, Why is none ſo fooliſh to reproue vs, &amp; ſay we lie in ſo ſaying? but becauſe we call theſe dayes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſimilitude of thoſe in which theſe things were done, ſo that it is called the ſame day, which is not the ſame, but by the courſe of time is like that, and it is ſaid to bee done that day for the miniſtring of the Sacrament, which was not done that day, but long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Was not Chriſt once offered in himſelfe? and yet in the Sacrament not onely at all the ſolemnities of Eaſter, but euery day he is offered to the people. And hee lieth not, that being asked the queſtion, doeth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that he is offered: For if the Sacraments ſhould not haue a certaine likeneſſe of thoſe things whereof they be Sacraments, they ſhould be no Sacraments at all. And of this likeneſſe, they take the names often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alſo of the things themſelues. Euen as therefore after a certaine ſort, the Sacrament of the body of Chriſt is the body of Chriſt, and the ſacrament of the blood of Chriſt, is the blood of Chriſt: ſo alſo the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of faith is faith. We ſee alſo in this place, that the proper body of Chriſt which was once offered, is diſcerned from that ſacrament which is daily offered, and after a ſort is the body.</p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>S. Auguſtin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrat. dist. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> as it is to be found <hi>De conſecrat. diſt. 2.</hi> Whether is this myſticall ſacrament of the cup vnder a figure, or vnder the trueth? The trueth ſaith, <hi>My fleſh is verily meat, and my blood is verily drinke,</hi> elſe how ſhall it be a great matter; <hi>The bread which I will giue is my fleſh for the life of the world,</hi> vnleſſe it be very
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1338:18"/>
fleſh in deed? But becauſe it is not lawfull to deuoure Chriſt with teeth, the Lords will was that this bread and wine ſhould be made potentially in a myſterie, his fleſh and blood verily by the conſecration of the holy Ghoſt, and ſhould be daily offered myſticallie for the life of the world: That euen as very fleſh was made of the Virgin by the holy Ghoſt, without the company of man; ſo alſo by the ſame through the ſubſtance of bread and wine, the ſame body is myſticallie conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The body of Chriſt is both trueth and a figure; Trueth, while the body and blood of Chriſt, by the power of the holy Ghoſt in power of the ſame, is made of the ſubſtance of bread and wine: but the figure is that which is outwardly ſeene.</p>
            <p>Here alſo <hi>Auguſtin</hi> doeth put a difference betweene the very fleſh taken of the Virgin, and the trueth of the fleſh that is made of the ſubſtance of bread and wine: for this (ſaith he) is daily created his very fleſh, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in myſterie, which thing is not lawfull to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the very proper body of Chriſt. The ſame au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in the ſame booke, Vntill the end of the world the Lord is aboue: but yet the trueth of the Lord is for all that here with vs. For it is fit that the body wherein hee roſe againe ſhould bee in one place, but the trueth thereof is ſpread euery where. Doeth he not plainely teach, that the body wherein hee roſe againe is one, which neceſſarily muſt be contained in one place, and that the trueth of his body is another, which is ſo farre ſpred abroad, as the ſacrament is rightly miniſtred?</p>
            <p>Here is moreouer to be noted, that the trueth of the Lords body is ſpoken two wayes, and ought two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner wayes to bee vnderſtood; for one maner of trueth of his body is required in myſterie, another ſimply and without myſterie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:1338:18"/>Thoſe words alſo of <hi>Augustin</hi> in the ſame place,<note place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>De conſecrat. diſt. 2. Vtrum ſub figura, &amp;c.</hi> doe make for this purpoſe; That becauſe we do now take the ſimilitude of his death in our Baptiſme, ſo alſo wee may take the ſimilitude of his fleſh and blood, ſo that the trueth ſhould not be wanting in the ſacrament, and yet be no laughing ſtocke to the Infidels for drinking the blood of a man ſlaine. He affirmeth the likeneſſe of fleſh and blood to be coupled with the trueth in the ſacrament: yet ſo as if one would vnderſtand it properly to be the blood of a man ſlaine, wee drinke it not: for ſo might the infidels laugh vs to ſcorne.</p>
            <p>He againe in the ſame title, <hi>Hoc est quod &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note> Euen as therefore the heauenly bread, which is the fleſh of Chriſt after his ſort, is called the body of Chriſt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as indeed it is the ſacrament of Chriſts body, namely of that which was to be ſeene, handled, mortall, ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſſe; and the ſacrifice of the fleſh which is made by the hands of the Prieſt, is called the paſsion of Chriſts death and crucifying, not in very deed, but by the ſignification of the myſterie: ſo the ſacrament of faith which is meant Baptiſme, is faith. Againe he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth plainely, that the body of Chriſt which is to be ſeene and felt is one thing, and that another, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his ſort is called the body of Chriſt, whereas indeed it is a ſacrament of that body of his which is to be ſeen and felt.<note place="margin">Gloſſa ibidem.</note> Whereupon the Gloſſe vpon the ſame place hath thus, The heauenly bread (that is to ſay) the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ſacrament which doth truely repreſent the fleſh of Chriſt, is called the body of Chriſt, but vnproperly; and therefore it is called after a peculiar maner, not in the trueth of the matter, but by the ſignification of the myſterie. And a little before,<note place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note> the ſame Gloſſe ſaith in the ſame place; The heauenly ſacrament which is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1338:19"/>
the Altar is vnproperly called the body of Chriſt, euen as Baptiſme is vnproperly called faith.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">August. ad Dard.</note>To this agree thoſe wordes that the ſame <hi>Auguſtin</hi> writeth to <hi>Dardanus</hi> in this wiſe: Keepe faithfully the Chriſtian profeſsion, That hee roſe againe from the dead, He aſcended into heauen, Sitteth on the Right-hand of the Father: Neither ſhall he come from any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place then from thence to iudge the quicke and the dead; And ſo ſhal he come, (the voice of the Angel being witneſſe) as hee was ſeene to goe into heauen, namely in the ſame forme and ſubſtance of fleſh: vnto the which fleſh hee hath aſſuredly giuen immortalitie, and not taken away the nature. After this forme he is not to be thought that he is euery where ſpred abroad: For we muſt take heed that wee affirme not ſo the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie of his manhood, that wee take away the trueth of his body.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note>Afterward in the end of the ſame Epiſtle; Doubt not that Chriſt our Lord the onely begotten Sonne of God, equall to the Father, euen that Sonne of man which is leſſe then the Father, is both altogether pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent euery where as God, and alſo in ſome certaine place of heauen, for the meaſure of his true body. The trueth of Chriſts body, which in another place he ſaid is euery where ſpred abroad when hee ſpeaketh of the ſacrament of his body, here where he entreateth of his true body indeed properly vnderſtood, he denieth that according to that maner of body it is euery where ſpred abroad, but that ſo the trueth of his body is cleane taken away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtin</hi> is not contrary to himſelfe, but ſheweth plainely ynough that the body, and the trueth of the body is to be taken two waies. Peraduenture I ſeeme to haue rehearſed ouer many places out of <hi>Auſtin,</hi> but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1338:19"/>
yet this one place doe I thinke not to bee ouerpaſſed, which he hath left in writing vpon the Goſpel of <hi>Iohn tract. 50. The poore haue ye alwayes with you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem in Ioan. tract. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but me ſhall you not haue alwayes.</hi> Let good men receiue this alſo, and not bee troubled: for hee ſpake of the preſence of his body. For according to his Maieſtie, according to his prouidence, according to his vnſpeakeable and inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible grace, that is fulfilled which was ſaid by him, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde I am with you euery day, euen to the ende of the world.</hi> But according to the fleſh, which the Word tooke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, according to that that he was borne of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, according to that, that hee was taken of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that he was nailed to a tree, that hee was taken downe from the Croſſe, that he was wrapped in linen clothes, that he was layed in the graue, that hee appeared in his reſurrection, ye ſhall not alvvayes haue him with you. Why? Becauſe according to the preſence of his body, hee was conuerſant vvith his diſciples fourtie dayes, and they being in company vvith him, by ſeeing him and not follovving him, he aſcended into heauen, and is not here, for he is there, he ſitteth on the Right-hand of the Father: and here hee is alſo, for the preſence of his Maieſtie did not depart. After another ſort accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the preſence of his Maieſtie, we haue Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes. According to the preſence of his fleſh it vvas rightly ſaid to the diſciples, <hi>but mee ſhall you not haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes:</hi> for the Church had him a few dayes according to the preſence of his fleſh, and now keepeth him by faith, and ſeeth him not with eyes. Thus much out of <hi>Auguſtin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſpeaketh of that which is properly called Chriſts body, he denieth that it is ſimply preſent here, and doeth refuſe ſuch a preſence of his body: but when he ſpeaketh of the Sacrament, hee doeth affirme
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1338:20"/>
that his body is verily preſent, and a true preſence of his body, yet not properly, but, as he himſelfe doeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct vs, according to his Maieſtie, according to his vnſpeakeable &amp; inuiſible grace, whereof we wil ſpeake more at large hereafter. It is plaine therefore, that the body of Chriſt in the ſacrament is to bee vnderſtood one way, and that an other way which of neceſsitie muſt be in ſome place of heauen, for the fourmes ſake of a true body, as hee ſaith. Now let vs goe forward to other.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gregor. Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anz. oratione de Paſch.</note>
               <hi>Gregorie Nazianzene</hi> in his Oration of the feaſt of Eaſter, ſaith thus, But let vs be made partakers of the Paſſeouer, but yet ſtill figuratiuely, albeit this Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be more manifeſt then the old. For truly the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer of the Law (I ſpeake boldly) was a more darke figure of a figure: but within a while wee ſhall enioy it more perfect and manifeſt, when the Sonne the Word it ſelfe, ſhall drinke it new with vs in the kingdome of his Father, opening and teaching vs thoſe things which he hath now ſhewed ſparingly. Here <hi>Nazianzene</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſacrament of Thankeſgiuing a more manifeſt Paſſeouer then the Paſſeouer of the Law: yet ſtill for all that a figure, namely of that which wee ſhall enioy more perfit and manifeſt in the kingdome of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This Paſſeouer therefore which is performed in myſterie, doeth differ from that which remaineth for euer, wherewith wee ſhall bee ſatisfied in the world to come.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gregor. in hom. Paſch.</note>The other <hi>Gregorie</hi> in his Homily of the Paſſeouer: This wholeſome ſacrifice doeth renew to vs by a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie the death of the onely begotten Sonne: which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he riſing againe from death dieth no more, nor death ſhall haue any more dominion ouer him, yet hee liuing immortally, and vncorruptibly in himſelfe, dieth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1338:20"/>
againe in this myſterie, and his body is alſo receiued e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where, and his fleſh for the health of the people, his blood is not now ſhed into the hands of the vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but is powred out in the mouth of the faithfull. By this therefore we may iudge what maner of ſacrament this is, which for our abſolution doeth alwayes repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Paſsion of the onely begotten Sonne. For what faithfull man can doubt, that in the very houre of the ſacrifice, at the voyce of the Prieſt, the heauens open, and the company of Angels be preſent in the myſterie of Ieſus Chriſt? This <hi>Gregorie</hi> maketh a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene this ſacrifice, and the other, and doeth alſo ſhew that this death, this paſsion, this body, which things be done in this myſterie, doe repreſent and imitate thoſe things which were done long agoe. For if you follow the letter, his body is not ſpred out euery where, nor his fleſh ſuffereth, nor dieth any more, although theſe things be ſaid to be done in myſterie.</p>
            <p>The ſame opinion had <hi>Euſebius Emiſsenus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. Emiſ. de conſecrat. dist. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> whoſe wordes are rehearſed <hi>De conſecrat. Diſt. 2.</hi> as followeth. Foraſmuch as hee would take away from the eyes the body taken of the Virgin, and would place it aboue the ſtarres; it was neceſſary that in the day of his Supper, the ſacrament of his body and blood ſhould bee conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated vnto vs, to the end that that might be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped continually by a myſterie, which was once offered for a ranſome: that ſeeing a dayly and vnceaſing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption did runne for the ſaluation of all men, there might be a continuall oblation of redemption, and that continuall ſacrifice might liue in memorie, and might euer be preſent in grace, a true, perfect, and onely ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to be eſteemed in faith, not to bee iudged by forme nor by outward ſight, but by the inward affection. Whereupon the heauenly authoritie confirmeth, that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1338:21"/>
               <hi>My fleſh is verily meat; and my blood is verily drinke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let all doubt therefore of vnfaithfulnes depart, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he that is the author of the gift, the ſame is witnes of the trueth: for the inuiſible Prieſt by his word and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret power, turneth the viſible creature, into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of his body and blood, ſaying, <hi>Take, eate, this is my body,</hi> and after the bleſsing being repeated, <hi>Take and drinke</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>this is my blood.</hi> Therefore euen as at the becke of the Lord commanding it, ſuddenly, and of nothing the hie heauens, the depth of the waters, and largeneſſe of the earth was made: ſo by the like power in ſpiritual ſacraments, where power doeth command, effect doth obey. By plaine words doth <hi>Euſebius</hi> teach vs, that the proper body which he termeth taken vpon him, is not in the ſacrament, but withdrawen from the earth, placed aboue the ſtarres: and therefore is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the ſacrament of the body, wherein is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ſubſtance of the body, yet in a myſterie and by grace, not that ſubſtance which hee ſaid before was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, which if it were preſent, the ſacrament were not needfull; but a ſpirituall ſubſtance, and fit for the ſacraments, whereupon hee alſo calleth the ſacraments ſpirituall. And leſt we ſhould imagine it a more groſſe ſubſtance then is fit, hee alledgeth foorthwith the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of regeneration, ſaying, How great benefit ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and worthy to be praiſed, the force of the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſsing doeth worke, and how it ought not to bee a new and vnpoſsible matter to thee, that earthly &amp; mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal things be changed into the ſubſtance of Chriſt, aske thy ſelfe that art new borne againe in Chriſt. Lately farre from life, a ſtranger from mercie, and inwardly a dead man, from the way of health thou waſt baniſhed; and ſuddenly profeſsing the Lawes of Chriſt, and by wholeſome myſteries renewed, thou haſt leapt into the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1338:21"/>
body of the Church, not by ſight, but by beleefe, and of the childe of perdition waſt thought worthy by a ſecret pureneſſe, to be the Sonne of God by adoption, abiding ſtill in the viſible meaſure, and made inuiſibly greater then thy ſelfe, without increaſe of quantitie. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou waſt the very ſelfe-ſame man before, yet by augmentation of faith, thou art become much o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe: for in the outward man nothing is added, and all in the inward man is cleane changed, and ſo man was made the ſonne of God, and Chriſt was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the minde of man. Euen as therefore without corporall feeling (the former baſeneſſe ſet apart) thou haſt ſuddenly put on a new dignitie; and as in this point that God hath healed thoſe things that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe in thee, put away thine infections, wiped away thy ſpots, thy eyes are not truſted vvithall, but thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſenſes: ſo when thou goeſt vp to the holy Altar, to be fed with the ſpirituall meat, behold in thy faith the holy body and blood of Chriſt, honour it, marueile at it, touch it with thy minde, take it in the hand of thy heart, and eſpecially receiue it, whole Chriſt, with the thirſtie draught of the inward man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> declareth by this ſimilitude, what maner of change is made in the ſacrament, how earthly things be turned into the ſubſtance of Chriſt, and what maner of ſubſtance that is: without doubt, like vnto that change wherewith wee be altered in our Baptiſme, and ſuch a ſubſtance as wee put on in the bath of Regeneration, when we be borne the children of God, and made a new creature, and new men, when we paſſe into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Church, where in our outward part nothing is changed, but all inwardly, and for that cauſe calleth he it ſpirituall food, which we behold in faith, touch with minde, take with the hand of our heart, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1338:22"/>
with the thirſtie draught of the inward man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist. ad Hebr. de conſecrat. dist. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>With this agreeth that that <hi>Ambroſe</hi> writeth vpon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> and is repeated <hi>De conſecrat dist. 2.</hi> In Chriſt was once a mighty ſacrifice offered for an euerlaſting Redemption: vvhat doe vve then? doe vve not dayly offer him? yes, but in remembrance of his death: and it is but one ſacrifice, not many: for Chriſt vvas once offered, and this ſacrifice is a paterne of that. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith plainely, that that true ſacrifice vvas once offered, but this ſacrifice is offered euery day: and hee declareth in vvhat ſort it is one ſacrifice, and not one, vvhen he ſaith that this is a paterne of that. The ſame man in his booke of Myſteries ſaith,<note place="margin">Idem in lib. de Myst.</note> In that ſacrament is Chriſt, becauſe it is the body of Chriſt: it is not then a corporall, but a ſpirituall food, vvhereupon the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle alſo ſaith of the figure of it, <hi>That our fathers did eate the ſame ſpirituall food,</hi> for the body of God is a ſpiritual body, the body of Chriſt is the body of the diuine ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Theſe things cannot be ſaid of Chriſtes true and proper body, namely, that it is a ſpirit: for a ſpirit hath not fleſh and blood, vvhich that body hath, as the Lord himſelfe did vvitneſſe before his diſciples, <hi>Feele yee, and ſee you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for a ſpirit hath not fleſh and bones, as you ſee me haue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem de Sacr. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Wherefore the ſame auctour <hi>De ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis lib. 4.</hi> ſaith thus: Thou ſeeſt therefore hovv mighty in operation the vvord of Chriſt is. If then there be ſo great force in the vvord of the Lord Ieſu, that thoſe things ſhould begin to be which were not: hovv much more is it of force, to make thoſe things remaine which were, and yet to change them into another thing? The heauen was not, the ſea was not, the earth was not. But hearken to him that ſaith, <hi>He ſpake the word and they were made, he commanded and they were created.</hi> Therefore that I may anſvvere thee, it was not the body of Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1338:22"/>
the conſecration, but after the conſecration I tell thee it is now the body of Chriſt. <hi>He ſpake the word and it was made, he commanded and it was created</hi> Thou waſt thy ſelf, but thou waſt an old creature; after thou waſt conſecrated, thou didſt beginne to be a new creature. Wilt thou know how new a creature? Euery one is (ſaith he) a new creature in Chriſt. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> taketh his argument <hi>à maiore,</hi> By the word of God new things are made: then is it no marueile, if things which now be, and remaine, are changed into another thing by his word, vvhich thing is done in Sacraments. Examples of the firſt are Heauen, the Sea, the Earth: of the later, man, which before he be regenerate is an old creature, but after regeneration, by force of the word, albeit he be the very ſame he vvas before, namely a man ſtill, yet he receiueth an invvard change, and of an old, is made a new creature.</p>
            <p>Like vnto this he affirmeth the change in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to bee, when as both bread remaineth, and yet getteth to it ſelfe a nevv ſubſtance (that is to ſay) a new dignitie. That ſame thing doth hee yet more fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound in his ſixt booke, writing thus:<note place="margin">Idem de ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Peraduenture thou mayeſt ſay, How is it very fleſh? for I ſee a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, I ſee not the trueth of blood in deed. Firſt of all, I told thee of the vvord of Chriſt, that it worketh as of force, to change and alter the appointed kindes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Moreouer, when the diſciples of Chriſt could not away with his talke, but hearing that hee vvould giue them his fleſh to eate, and his blood to drinke, went their way; yet <hi>Peter</hi> alone ſaid, <hi>Thou hast the words of eternall life, whither ſhall I goe from thee?</hi> Leaſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any moe ſhould ſo ſay, but the grace of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould remaine; Therefore thou takeſt the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in a ſimilitude, but thou doeſt attaine the grace
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1338:23"/>
and vertue of the true nature. At the laſt he addeth to make vp the matter; And thou which receiueſt bread, art made partaker in that ſpirituall food, of the diuine ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>We learne by the authoritie of this ſo great a man, that that which we take in the ſacrament, is a ſpiritual, not a corporall food; neither that that fleſh is to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken after the maner of his proper fleſh, as the <hi>Capernaits</hi> did, and vvith offence went backe, but together with the outvvard ſigne we obtaine the grace and vertue of the true nature, and receiuing the bread are partakers of his diuine ſubſtance. And here alſo we ſee that <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> was of the ſame opinion that <hi>Emiſſenus</hi> was, and far otherwiſe vnderſtandeth both the alteration which is made in the ſacraments, and alſo the very terme of ſubſtance, then it is either taken in proper ſpeach, or as Philoſophers do naturally ſpeake.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Idem de offic. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note>To the ſame purpoſe ſerueth alſo that which he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in his booke <hi>De officijs lib. 4. cap. 48.</hi> Here is the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovv, here is the image; there is the trueth: the ſhadow in the Lavv, the image in the Goſpel: but the trueth in heauen. In time paſt the Lambe was offered, the calfe vvas offered; Novv is Chriſt offered: but he is offered as man, as taking his Paſsion, but hee as a Prieſt doeth offer himſelfe here as in an image, but there in trueth, where hee maketh interceſsion for vs, as an aduocate vvith his Father. Hee putteth a difference in the one oblation from the other. And albeit both (after their maner) be done in deed, yet this vvhich is ſolemnized in the Church, is done in an Image, but the trueth it ſelfe remaineth as an Aduocate for vs vvith the Father.</p>
            <p>And this place of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> doeth ſeeme to be like to that place of <hi>Origen</hi> vpon the 38.<note place="margin">Origen in Pſal. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> Pſalme, vvhere he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth of that ſaying of <hi>Paul, For the Law hauing a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1338:23"/>
of thoſe good things to come, hath not the very Image of the things &amp;c.</hi> And thus he vvriteth: But if any man can paſſe from this ſhadovv, let him come to the Image of the things, and ſee the comming of Chriſt made in the fleſh; Let him behold that hie Prieſt, both novv offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſacrifices to the Father, &amp; that ſhall hereafter offer; And let him vnderſtand all theſe things to be the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of ſpirituall things, and that heauenly things be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by corporall Offices. It is therefore called an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage vvhich is receiued for the preſent time, and may be diſcerned by the nature of man. If thou canſt vvith thought and mind pearce the heauens, and follovv IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS vvho hath pearced the heauens, and is novv pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent before the face of God for vs, there ſhalt thou find thoſe good things of vvhich the Lavv had a ſhadovv, and Chriſt ſhevved the Image in the fleſh, vvhich are prepared for the bleſſed, vvhich neither eye hath ſeene, nor eare heard, nor aſcended into the heart of man: vvhich things vvhen thou ſhalt ſee, thou ſhalt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that he that vvalketh in them, and continueth in deſire and earneſt affection after them, ſuch a one vval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not novv in an Image, but in the very trueth it ſelfe. <hi>Origen</hi> writeth to the learned and practiſed, and therefore not eaſie to be vnderſtood of all men. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvithſtanding, he ſhevveth plainely that the ſacrifices vvhich be here offered, be Images of that trueth vvhich pearced to heauens, and abiding before the face of God is interceſſor for vs: And therefore that the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of the trueth be one thing, and the very trueth another. And that although theſe Images haue alſo their trueth, yet this differeth from that proper trueth vvhich vve ſhall there indeed attaine to, vvhen vve fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovving Chriſt, ſhall pearce the heauens vvhere hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth; the vvhich after a ſort vvee alſo enioy here,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1338:24"/>
while in our deuout meditations our mindes being lift vp to heauen, we behold thoſe ſecret good things. He alſo vpon <hi>Matthew cap. 15.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem in Mat. cap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> ſaith: Neither is it the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial bread, but the word that is ſpoken ouer it, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth to him that eateth not vnvvorthily of the Lord. And theſe things are ſpoken of the figuratiue and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall body.</p>
            <p>Many things beſide may be ſaid of the Word which was made fleſh. Here <hi>Origen</hi> doeth declare, that the true fleſh, (that is to ſay) the true nature of man, which Chriſt being the Word tooke vnto him, to bee one maner of fleſh, and an other thing to bee his figuratiue and ſymbolical body, with which words he calleth the Sacrament. To this purpoſe ſerue the wordes that he writeth <hi>Contra Celſum lib. 8.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem contra Celſum lib. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> We obeying the Maker of all things for his great benefits beſtovved vpon vs, when we haue giuen Thankes, are fed with the loaues ſet before vs, which by interceſsion and prayers are made a certaine more holy body. Theſe words, A cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain more holy body, do not agree to the proper body of Chriſt, but they agree to the ſacrament of Thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, which after a certaine maner is his body. The ſame man vpon <hi>Leuiticus Homil. 7.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem in Leuit. Homil. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> expoundeth the ſame matter more plainely, ſaying: But you if ye be the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Church, if you bee indued with the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Goſpel, if the Word made fleſh dvvelleth in you; acknowledge you theſe things which we ſpeake, that they be the Lords, leſt peraduenture he that is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, be ignorant ſtill: Acknowledge that they be fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures which be written in the holy Volumes, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore examine them as ſpiritual, &amp; not carnall men, and vnderſtand thoſe things which bee ſpoken: For if you take thoſe things as carnal men, they hurt you, and doe not nouriſh you. For there is alſo in the Goſpel a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1338:24"/>
that killeth: The killing letter is not onely found in the olde Teſtament. There is alſo a letter in the nevv Teſtament that can kill him which will not ſpiritually marke thoſe things that bee ſpoken. For if thou follow this that hath bene ſpoken, according to the letter, <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ye eat my fleſh and drinke my blood,</hi> this letter ſlayeth. Seeing then the Authors euery where referre theſe wordes to the ſacrament; and <hi>Origen</hi> commandeth ſo much to flee the letter, as to ſay that it killeth: Who ſeeth not, that Chriſtes fleſh is in the ſacrament one way to bee vnderſtood, and another according to the letter, and in proper ſpeech?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epiphanius in Anchor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to</hi> is of the ſame opinion,<note place="margin">Epiphanius in Anchorato.</note> where he ſaith: For wee ſee that our Sauiour tooke into his hands, as the Goſpel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taineth, that he roſe in the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and tooke theſe things, and when hee had giuen Thankes, he ſaid, <hi>This is mine, &amp;c.</hi> And we ſee that it is not equal, nor like, neither to the Image that is in fleſh, nor to his inuiſible Godhead, nor to the features of his members: for this is of a round faſhion and without ſence, as much as to the povver of it ſelfe appertaineth. And therefore his will was to ſpeake by grace, <hi>This is mine, &amp;c.</hi> And euery man beleeueth his ſaying: for he that beleeueth not that he is true as he hath ſaid, hee is fallen from grace and health. But that which we haue heard wee beleeue that it is his: for vve know that our Lord is altogether ſence, all indued with ſence, all God, all moouing, all working, all light, all incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible; but yet he, that hath giuen vs this with grace. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> doeth in this place endeuour himſelfe to proue, that man being made after the Image of God, hath in deed the Image of God, not according to the proper nature of diuinitie, but after grace; and vſeth the ſimilitude taken of the Sacrament of Thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1338:25"/>
the which according to the proper nature of a body, he denieth it to be the body of Chriſt, ſince it hath neither the forme of a true body, and lacketh fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and mouing, and yet it is verily beleeued to be his body by grace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cyprian de Coena D mini.</note>
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> alſo in his ſermon of the Supper of the Lord, doeth very godly and plentifully reaſon to the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, out of the which I haue thought ſufficient to touch theſe fevv places. For none of the Fathers haue more extolled the dignitie of the Sacrament, and ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out all carnall ſence, more plainely declared the true vnderſtanding of ſo great a myſterie. An vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming meat (ſaith hee) the Maſter did ſet before his diſciples: neither were the people bidden to a ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and cunningly dreſſed Banquet, but there is giuen an immortall food differing from common meates, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the ſhape of bodily ſubſtance, but prouing by inuiſible vvorking, that the diuine vertue is preſent. Againe, There did ſometime ariſe a queſtion (as it is read in the Goſpel of <hi>Iohn</hi>) of the noueltie of this word, and at the doctrine of this Myſterie were the hearers amazed, vvhen the Lord ſaid, <hi>Vnleſſe you eate of the fleſh of the Sonne of man, and drinke his blood, you ſhall not haue life in you:</hi> Becauſe certaine, for that they did not yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, nor could vnderſtand, went backe, for that it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to them an horrible and hainous thing to feed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mans fleſh, thinking hee had ſpoken this after that ſort, as though they ſhould haue bene taught to haue eaten his fleſh ſod, or roſted, and cut in pieces: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the fleſh of his perſon, if it ſhould bee deuided into morſels, could not haue bene ſufficient for all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, which being once ſpent, Religion ſhould ſeeme to periſh, vvhich ſhould not haue aftervvard a ſacrifice remaining any longer. But in ſuch like thoughts fleſh
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1338:25"/>
and blood profiteth nothing, becauſe as the Maſter himſelfe hath expounded, <hi>Theſe words be Spirit and life:</hi> neither doth the carnall ſenſe pearſe the vnderſtanding of ſo great a depth, vnleſſe Faith be added too. The Bread is food, the Blood is life, the Fleſh ſubſtance, the Body the Church. A body, becauſe of the agreeing of members in one; Bread, for the conformitie of nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment; Blood, for the effect of life giuen; Fleſh, for the propertie of the humanitie taken. Alſo hee ſayth, This common bread beeing changed into fleſh and blood, doeth procure life and encreaſe to the bodies, and therefore by the accuſtomed effect of things, the weakeneſſe of our faith is aided, and taught by a ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble argument, that the effect of eternall life is in the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Sacraments, and that we be knit to Chriſt not ſo much by corporall, as by ſpirituall paſſage. Alſo this bread which hee reached to his diſciples, beeing chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, not in forme but in nature, by the omnipotencie of the Word is made fleſh; and euen as in the perſon of Chriſt the humanitie was ſeene and the diuinitie hid, ſo into the viſible Sacrament vnſpeakeably doeth the diuine ſubſtance powre it ſelfe. Alſo the Maſter truely of this Inſtitution ſayd, that <hi>Vnleſſe wee ſhould eate and drinke his blood, we ſhould not haue life in vs:</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing vs by a ſpirituall leſſon, and opening our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to ſo hidden a matter, that wee ſhould knowe that our eating is an abiding in him, and our drinke as it were a certaine incorporation, by ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſeruice, and ioyning our willes, and vniting our affections. Alſo hee ſayth, Among the gueſts of the Lords table the natural man is not admitted; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer fleſh and blood doeth appoint is ſhut out from this company, it ſauoureth nothing, it profiteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, whatſoeuer the finenes of the ſence of man doth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1338:26"/>
goe about. <hi>Cyprian</hi> hath theſe and many other places to the ſame purpoſe. The very words of <hi>Cyprian</hi> doe ſufficiently declare that which belongeth to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: How the Letter is not to bee followed in theſe things which be ſpoken of this myſterie; how the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Fleſh is vtterly to be ſhunned, and all things to be referred to a ſpiritual ſenſe: That there is the preſence of the diuine power in this Bread, the effect of euerlaſting life, and that the diuine ſubſtance is powred thereinto; that the words are ſpirit and life, that a ſpirituall leſſon is giuen; that this Body, this Blood and Fleſh, this ſubſtance of body, ought not to be taken after a common ſort, nor as mans reaſon doth appoint, but to be named, thought of, beleeued for certaine excellent effects, powers and properties ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereto, which be euen within the body and blood of Chriſt by nature; namely, that it doeth both feede and reuiue our ſoules, and prepareth our bodies to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and immortalitie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cyrill. in Ioan. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note>The ſame opinion hath alſo <hi>Cyrillus,</hi> who though he affirme in many places, the trueth and nature of the body of Chriſt to be in the Sacrament; yet hee is in opinion, that it is a ſpiritual and diuine matter, and not to be vnderſtood after the manner of men. For firſt he declareth, that the ſame maner of eating is ſet foorth in the words of the Lords Supper, which the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſignified when he ſaid, <hi>Vnleſſe you eat the fleſh of the Sonne of man, &amp;c.</hi> For ſo he writeth in his 4. booke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 14. Chap. of <hi>Iohn:</hi> Where after he had ſpoken ſomewhat of them that did ſay, <hi>How can this man giue his fleſh to be eaten?</hi> hee addeth theſe words; Therefore they ought firſt to haue ſet the rootes of faith in their minde, and then to ſeeke for thoſe things that are to be ſought for of man: but they, before they would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1338:26"/>
did ſeeke importunately. For this cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the Lord did not open, how it might be, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth to ſeeke it by faith. So to his diſciples that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, he gaue the pieces of bread, ſaying, <hi>Take ye, and eate ye, this is my body.</hi> The cup alſo in like maner he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about, ſaying, <hi>Drinke yee all of this: This is the cup of my blood, which ſhall be ſhed for many for the remiſsion of ſins.</hi> Thou ſeeſt manifeſtly, that by no meanes he would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the maner of the myſterie to them that ſought it without faith: but to them that did beleeue, and did not ſeeke it, he plainely declared it. Likewiſe in cap. 21.<note place="margin">Idem in cap. <hi>21</hi>
               </note> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe words, <hi>This is a hardſaying,</hi> thus he ſaith: And ſuch as want ſharpeneſſe of wit, are wont to abhorre knowledge, which ſhould be ſought with great ſtudy, and much labour: but yet the ſpirituall man accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the Lords doctrine, as to great dainties, doth continually ſing, <hi>How ſweet be thy words vnto my throat! yea aboue hony to my mouth.</hi> But the naturall Iew doeth thinke this ſpirituall myſterie full of fooliſhneſſe; and where by the Lords words he is ſtirred to an higher vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of things, yet he falleth ſtill to his accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med madneſſe. Likewiſe in his cap. 22. expounding theſe words, <hi>Doeth this offend you?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem in cap. <hi>22</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hee writeth on this ſort. For ignorance, many which followed Chriſt, not vnderſtanding his words, were troubled: for when they heard him ſay, <hi>Verely, verely, I ſay vnto you, vnleſſe ye eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man, and drinke his blood, you ſhall not haue life in you,</hi> they thought Chriſt had cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them to the cruel maners of beaſts, and ſtirred them to eate the rawe fleſh of a man, and to drinke blood, which be euen horrible to heare. For they had not yet knowen the maner of this myſterie, and the godly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration thereof. Alſo in the 24. chapter.<note place="margin">Idem cap. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> The words therefore that I haue ſpoken to you bee ſpirit, that is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1338:27"/>
ſpirituall, and of the ſpirit, and life, that is to ſay, they be of the liuely and naturall life.<note place="margin">Idem ad Calo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrium.</note> The ſame mans words are rehearſed to <hi>Caloſyrius,</hi> which follow. For leaſt we ſhould abhorre fleſh and blood ſet vpon the holy Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, God fauouring our frailty, powred into the things offered the power of life, turning them into the trueth of his owne fleſh, that a body of life, as it were a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſeed that giueth life, might be found in vs.</p>
            <p>By theſe and many other places in <hi>Cyrillus,</hi> we be lift vp from the letter to the ſpirite, from the ſence of the naturall man, to a more hie vnderſtanding of a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all myſterie. It muſt not be thought here, that we eate the rawe fleſh of a man, or drinke his blood, but that the words bee ſpirituall, and ſpiritually to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that they be termed fleſh and blood, but ought to be vnderſtood of ſpirit and life, that is to ſay, of the vertue of the Lords fleſh that giueth life: And therfore ſaide hee that the povver of life was put into the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſignes,<note place="margin">Idem in Ioan. lib. <hi>11.</hi> cap. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> and called it by an apt ſignification the body of life. The ſame man vpon <hi>Iohn lib. 11. cap. 26.</hi> doth expound ſomewhat more plainely, how wee be coupled corporally both with Chriſt and with our ſelues, and that by the partaking of the ſacrament, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we be ſeuered both in body and ſoule. It muſt be conſidered, ſaith he, whether to the vnitie of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and will wee may alſo finde a naturall vnity, by which we ſhall be lincked among our ſelues, and we all vnto God. For peraduenture we are ioyned alſo with corporall vnion, although we be ſeuered one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, that ech one apart hath his being and diſtance of place. For although <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> be one by vnity in Chriſt, yet <hi>Peter</hi> is not <hi>Paul.</hi> Afterward within few words hee thus concludeth; The originall therefore, and the way whereby wee bee partakers of the holy
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1338:27"/>
Ghoſt, and vnited to God, is the myſterie of Chriſt, for we bee all ſanctified in him. Therefore, that hee might vnite vs one to another, and euery one to God, although we bee ſeuered both in body and ſoule, yet hath hee found a vvay agreeable to the counſell of his Father, and to his ovvne wiſedome. For hee bleſsing thoſe as beleeue, with his body, through the myſticall communion doeth make vs both with himſelfe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo among our ſelues, one body. It is plaine that <hi>Cyrillus</hi> ſpake not of the ſame kind of body, when he ſaith, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they bee ſeuered in body and ſoule, yet they which beleeue, through the body of Chriſt, and by the myſticall communion be made one body with Chriſt, and betvveene themſelues. For euen as the faithfull, being ioyned in that ſpirituall body, are one body, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though their proper bodies remaine ſeuered: Euen ſo alſo wee being ioyned with Chriſt in that ſpirituall body, are made one body with him, although his ovvne proper body bee farre diſtant from our bodies. Let vs adde one place more taken out of this Father,<note place="margin">Idem in lib. ad Euop. Anat. <hi>11</hi>
               </note> which is in his booke <hi>Ad Euoptium Anath. 11.</hi> where he ſpeaketh thus of <hi>Nestorius.</hi> Doeth not he pronounce this myſterie to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is a deuouring of mans fleſh, and violently driue the mindes of the faithfull, without conſcience, into falſe interpretations, and with mans inuentions take thoſe things in hand, which are receiued by an onely pure, and vnſearchable faith? <hi>Cyrillus</hi> doth in this place obiect againſt <hi>Nestorius,</hi> That to maintaine this error, he did ſpeake too groſly of the Sacrament, as though the faithfull doe properly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in eate mans fleſh, which by the Greeke word hee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: But ſuch kind of thoughts hee termeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſay, as <hi>Budaeus</hi> doeth interpret it, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeite, not right, not ſincere: For ſo much as here is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1338:28"/>
no place for ſuch kinde of worldly and common ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations.</p>
            <p>We ought to thinke the like of <hi>Theophylactus,</hi> who although in ſome place he may ſeeme to haue follovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a more groſſe opinion, as vpon <hi>Matthew</hi> the 26. Chapter, whoſe words wee haue aboue rehearſed, wherein he ſeemeth to denie, that the bread of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of thankeſgiuing, is a figure of the Lords bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but the very body indeede; yet when he ſaith, It is no figure, he meaneth that it is not onely a figure, as in another place, where vpon <hi>Marke</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> it is read: for elſe hee ſhould haue repugned againſt all the olde Writers (and that is not likely) who throughout, terme this Sacrament a figure, an image, a ſigne and patterne. Beſides, in that he ſaid it was the body in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deede, his meaning was not to haue it taken after a worldly and common ſort, as it ſhall manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by thoſe things that follow: for he writing vpon theſe words in the ſixt Chapter of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theophylac. in Ioan. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Iewes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did ſtriue among themſelues, ſaying, How can this man giue vs his fleſh to eate?</hi> ſaith thus: It behoueth vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, after that wee heare, <hi>vnleſſe yee eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man, yee ſhall haue no life,</hi> in taking the heauenly myſteries to keepe ſtedfaſt and vnwauering faith, and not to be inquiſitiue how. For the naturall man, that is, hee that follovveth mans carnall and naturall thoughts, is not apt to conceiue ſuch matters as bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue nature and ſpirituall, and euen ſo he doth not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the ſpirituall eating of the Lords fleſh, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of who ſo bee not partakers, ſhall not bee partakers of euerlaſting life. And by and by hee expoundeth thus theſe words, <hi>Hee that eateth my fleſh, &amp;c.</hi> In this place vve learne the Sacrament of the communion. For he that eateth and drinketh the Lords fleſh and blood,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1338:28"/>
abideth in the Lord himſelfe, and the Lord in him: for there is a new mixture made, and aboue reaſon, ſo that God is in vs, and wee in God. Here the Author tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that faith muſt be had in the myſteries, and not to be inquiſitiue how: and therewithall he remoueth apart mans carnall or naturall thoughts, and requireth onely a ſpirituall meaning, and commendeth a more hie maner of eating. For he addeth not long after vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe words, <hi>This is a hard ſaying, who can heare him? &amp;c.</hi> But ſee their folly; For their duetie had been, to haue asked, and learned thoſe things whereof they were ignorant. But they drew backe, and did expound nothing ſpiritually, but all things as they outwardly appeared. For in as much as they heard of fleſh, they thought he would compell them to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, deuourers of fleſh and blood. But becauſe we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it ſpiritually, neither wee bee deuourers of fleſh, and yet be we ſanctified by ſuch meate. By and by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo expounding this, <hi>It is ſpirit that quickeneth,</hi> thus he writeth: Becauſe, as we haue often ſayd, they that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally expounded ſuch things as Chriſt ſpake, were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended: he ſayth, When thoſe things that I ſpeake are ſpiritually vnderſtood, that onely bringeth profit: but the fleſh, that is to ſay, to expound them carnally, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth nothing, but is occaſion of offence. So there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch as heard carnally thoſe things that Chriſt ſpake, were offended. He addeth therefore, <hi>The words which I ſpeake are ſpirit,</hi> that is to ſay, they be ſpirituall, <hi>and life,</hi> (hauing nothing that is carnall) and bringing euerlaſting life. Let vs adde hereunto thoſe things which he writeth vpon Marke 14. cap. 1. For the bread is not onely a figure, and a certaine patterne of the Lords body, but it is turned into the very body of Chriſt. For the Lord ſayth, <hi>The bread which I will giue,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1338:29"/>
is my fleſh.</hi> And againe, <hi>Vnleſſe ye eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man, &amp;c.</hi> And how, ſaith he, is not the fleſh ſeene? O man, this is done for our infirmitie. For ſince the bread and wine bee of thoſe things which we be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted withall, we abhorre them not: but if wee ſhould ſee blood and fleſh ſet before vs, we could not abide it, but ſhould vtterly abhorre it. Therefore God of his mercie fauouring our frailtie, retaineth ſtill the forme of bread and wine, but he altereth the element into the power of fleſh and blood. By all theſe places it is moſt certaine, that <hi>Theophylactus</hi> followed the ſteps of the ancient fathers, ſet aſide all carnall imaginations in this Sacrament, &amp; called vs to ſuch as be hie and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, that it is not only a figure of the Lords bodie, but rather is verely his body, &amp; yet they that be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers are not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſay, fleſh eaters: And he addeth the cauſe, for that we vnderſtand it not carnally but ſpiritually, that is to ſay, that they remaine the formes of bread and wine, but yet do paſſe into the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the Lords fleſh and blood, and, as he tearmed it, be tranſelemented, in which tearme there is no cauſe why we ſhould faine to our ſelfe any Popiſh Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation as they cal it.<note place="margin">Idem in Ioan. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> For writing vpon the 6. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Iohn,</hi> he vſeth the ſame terme, ſaying thus: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euen as I, ſaith he, liue for the Father, that is, as I am borne of the Father, which is life: euen ſo alſo, he that eateth me, liueth by the meanes of me, while he is after a ſort mixed with me, and is tranſelemented into me that can quicken. By this terme of tranſelementatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he meant to ſignifie nothing els, but the ſame change that is fit for the Sacraments: wherof <hi>Ambroſe, Emiſſenus</hi> and others make mention, as before we haue repeated: for otherwayes wee cannot be tranſelemented into Chriſt. And no maruell that <hi>Theophylactus</hi> ſo tearmed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1338:29"/>
it, ſince <hi>Chryſostom</hi> himſelfe vpon the ſixt chap. of <hi>Iohn, homilia 45.</hi> vſeth theſe wordes:<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Ioan. cap. <hi>6.</hi> homil. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> But that we ſhould not onely by loue, but alſo in very deed bee turned into that fleſh, hee hath wrought it by the meate which hee hath giuen vs. Behold, <hi>Chryſostome</hi> ſaith, we are turned into the fleſh of Chriſt really, as I may ſo terme it: But yet who ſeeth not that turning to be ſpirituall, not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal? Euen ſo is bread turned in very deede, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elemented into Chriſtes fleſh, but by a ſpiritual and no carnall turning, becauſe the bread doeth get to it the power of the fleſh. And theſe things which haue bene thus cited out of <hi>Theophylactus,</hi> albeit he be not ſo anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent an authour, yet becauſe hee is chiefly alleaged of ſuch as followe the carnall ſence in the ſacrament of thankeſgiuing, though hee doth very manifeſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound himſelfe, and teacheth nothing repugnant to holy Scriptures and writings of old Authors, I meant to ſhew the true opinion of ſo learned a man, and not to diſcredit his authoritie as a late writer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Damaſcenus</hi> is yet vnſpoken of, whom the aduerſaries vſe as it were a chief champion: but in caſe they would not ſnatchingly picke out ſuch ſentences as ſerue the humor of their affections, but marke well the through drift of his writing; he helpeth not ſo much their cauſe as he doth ouerthrow it. Albeit (that I may frankely admoniſh the reader and vtter mine opinion) he is but a very ſlippery and an vncertain author in expounding of this myſterie, and none, I dare ſay, among the olde writers, ſhall be found, that hath reaſoned of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo obſcurely and doubtfully. Truely I gather by him, that vvhen hee had determined to write a breuiat of the true faith, hee vvould neither leaue this ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnſpoken of, nor yet vviſt how to intreate of it plainely enough: The vvhich of his ovvne vvords the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1338:30"/>
indifferent reader ſhall eaſily iudge.<note place="margin">Damaſ. De fide Orthod. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> He vvriteth <hi>De fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de orthod. lib. 4. cap. 14.</hi> of Chriſt in this vviſe: It behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, not onely that the firſt fruits of our nature ſhould come into the partaking of a better, but that all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as many as would, ſhould both be borne by a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond natiuitie, and nouriſhed with a nevv meat, meet for that natiuity, and ſo preuent the meaſure of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And a litle after: And becauſe he is a ſpirituall Adam, it behoued the natiuitie alſo to be ſpirituall, and likewiſe the meate. For ſince vvee haue a double and compound nature, it is fitte that the natiuitie bee alſo double, and the food likevviſe compound. The nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie therefore is giuen vs by vvater and ſpirit, I meane by holy Baptiſme: but the meate is our Lord himſelfe Ieſus Chriſt, vvhich came dovvne from heauen. Then after alleaging the vvordes of the Lords Supper, and proofes of vvhat force the vvord is, he addeth: Euen as all things vvhatſoeuer God had made, he hath made them by the vvorking of the holy Ghoſt: ſo novv alſo the ſame force of the holy Ghoſt bringeth to paſſe thoſe things that be aboue nature, the vvhich no thing can comprehend but onely faith. And a little after: But bread and vvine bee taken: For God knovveth mans vveakenes: For commonly thoſe things vvhich it is not acquainted vvith, it ſhunneth vvith loathſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Therfore he humbled himſelfe after his wonted maner, and bringeth to paſſe by the accuſtomed things of nature, ſuch things as bee aboue nature. And euen as in Baptiſme, becauſe it is the maner of men to bee waſhed vvith vvater, and anointed vvith oyle, he cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled vvith oile and vvater the grace of the holy Ghoſt, and made it to be the vvaſhing of regeneration: After the ſame ſort, becauſe men are vvont to eate bread and drinke vvine and vvater, he coupled therevvithall his
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1338:30"/>
Diuinitie, and made them his body and blood, that by matters vſuall and agreeable to nature, we may be cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to thoſe things which paſſe nature. Hitherto hee ſeemed to agree with the reſt; for ſuch as the ſecond natiuitie is, ſuch, ſaith he, is the meate: He termeth the natiuitie ſpirituall, likewiſe alſo the meat: The natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be double, through water and the holy Ghoſt, the meat alſo double: but how it is double hee allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth not forthwith, as hee did in the natiuity, but the meate, ſaith he, is the very bread of life which came downe from heauen: yet after a few wordes he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth howe it is done, ſaying, As the water is coupled with the grace of the holy Ghoſt, and is made the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of regeneration: ſo is the diuinitie coupled with the bread, and is made the body &amp; blood of the Lord. And this hee affirmeth to be the working of the holy Ghoſt, and that the bread and wine be taken for mans infirmitie, and by matters vſual to nature, thoſe things bee wrought that paſſe nature, which onely faith can comprehend. None of theſe things be contrary to the opinion of the other Fathers: but thoſe things that follow be not ſo. It is verely his body, ſaith he, that is knit with the diuinitie, that body taken of the holy Virgin. This before him no man had ſaid. If his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning be of the proper body, the authoritie of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that were before him cryeth out againſt him, which plainely affirme that body to be taken from the earth, caried aboue the ſtarres, and not to be here: who alſo with manifeſt difference doe ſeparate that body from the ſacrament of the bodie, vnleſſe peraduenture we may ſo interprete it, as that ſaying of <hi>Augustine,</hi> The ſame body, and not the ſame body: the ſame by grace and power, and not the ſame according to the proper maner of a body: the which it may ſeeme that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1338:31"/>
this Authors meaning was when he writ this. For by and by there followeth: Not that the body that was taken of the Virgin, ſhould come down from heauen, but that the very bread and wine is chaunged into the body and blood of the Lord. By which woords hee himſelfe teſtifieth, that this body which is receiued in the Sacrament, is to bee vnderſtood one way, and that body which was taken, which hee denieth to come downe from heauen, another way. For if it abide in heauen without comming downe hither; and if bread be made of the very ſame body that was taken; ſure the bread muſt be in heauen, and the faithfull ſhall here receiue neither the bread nor yet the body, which thing no man in his right wits can affirme. But if wee leaue the body that was taken in his place in heauen, as our faith doth require, and ſay notwithſtanding that the ſame is preſent in the ſacrament by grace and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as the reſt of the Fathers do pronounce, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this bread may be called and beleeued for the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall propertie of a body that is coupled with it, to be the body of Chriſt, not properly as that body that he tooke vpon him, but after a ſpirituall ſort, as the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that body; the matter is not intricate, but plainely opened, neither ſhall there bee any neede to frame crooked mazes that be cleane contrary to our faith, or to knit vaine ropes of ſand, or to ſhun the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes that the former Fathers vſed, and to inuent other ſimilitudes groſſe and ſtrange from myſteries, as <hi>Damaſcenus</hi> doth in this place. For euen as (ſaith hee) the bread in eating, and the wine and water in drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are naturally turned into the body and blood of him that eateth and drinketh them, and be made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther body, then that they had before: ſo the Shewe bread, and the wine and water by inuocation and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1338:31"/>
comming of the holy Ghoſt, bee changed aboue the law of nature, into the body and blood of Chriſt, and be not two but one and the ſame. What other thing doeth hee by this ſimilitude, but open a way to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, the eating of mans fleſh, which thing <hi>Cyrillus, Theophylactus</hi> and other Fathers do deteſt? How much better haue <hi>Cyprian, Ambroſe, Epiphanius, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsenus,</hi> and other ſaid, which affirme a like change in the ſacrament of thankeſgiuing, as that which is made in Baptiſme? whereby it commeth to paſſe, that the ſignes do remaine the ſame, and by grace they get to themſelues a new ſubſtance in like maner, as one ſelfe man being not yet regenerate doeth belong to the olde Adam, and after regeneration becommeth a new man, and a new creature, not by a fleſhly meane, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth not to ſacraments, but after a ſpirituall ſort.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Damaſcenus</hi> forgetting himſelfe, who had before affirmed this meate to be ſpirituall, as the regeneration in Baptiſme; now teacheth it to be carnall, if this bread muſt paſſe into the body of Chriſt, as common bread doth into the bodies of thoſe that eate it: vvhereby it happeneth, that he falleth alſo into another errour: for he denieth this bread and wine to bee a figure. This bread and wine (ſaith he) is not a figure of the body and blood of Chriſt, God forbid, but the very deified body of the Lord. And no marueile it is that he denieth this, if he be in opinion that this bread is ſo changed as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bread is into the body of the feeder. But all they of old time throughout be repugnant: and ſurely hee iarreth with himſelfe: for after thoſe wordes cited out of the ſixt Chapter of Iohn, <hi>Vnleſſe yee eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>My fleſh verely, &amp;c.</hi> by and by he bringeth another ſimilitude of a coale, farre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe from the former. A coale (ſaith he) is not ſimple
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1338:32"/>
wood, but coupled with fire: ſo the bread of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is not ſimple bread, but coupled with the diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. How diuers is the maner of theſe two ſimilitudes? before he ſaid, that the Shewbread was turned into the body of Chriſt, beyond nature, as the common bread is naturally changed into the body of him that eateth it, but that is not done vvhile there remaineth bread: here he ſaith, that the bread of communion is not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple bread, but bread coupled with the diuinitie. The bread therefore remaineth: to what is it coupled? to the diuinitie. Where is then that groſſe tranſmutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Againe a litle after: This is that pure ſacrifice without blood, which God hath commanded by the Prophet ſhould be offered to himſelfe, from the riſing of the Sunne, to the going dovvne of the ſame. If hee ſpeake of the body that hee tooke vpon him, how is it without blood? if hee ſpeake of his ſpirituall body and blood, he ſaith trueth. Againe he ſaith: This body is not conſumed, it is not corrupted, nor caſt into the draught. If his meaning be of his ſpirituall and better ſubſtance of the ſacrament, vvee confeſſe it: if of the outward ſigne, <hi>Origen</hi> farre better learned then <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcenus</hi> ſaith, As touching to that material part that it hath, it goeth into the belly, and is caſt into the draught. <hi>Damaſcenus</hi> goeth yet further and ſaith, The bread is the firſt fruites of the bread to come, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <hi>epiouſios</hi> doth ſignifie either the bread to come, that is of the world to come, or els that which is taken for the conſecration of our ſubſtance. But vvhether it be this way or that way, it is aptly called the body of Chriſt. For the Lords fleſh is a ſpirit giuing life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was conceiued of a quickening ſpirit. For that which is borne of ſpirit, is ſpirit. But this I ſpeake not, to take away the nature of a body, but willing to ſhew
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1338:32"/>
his quickening and diuinitie. How changeable is this ſpeach? ſometime one and the ſelfe bread is one and ſelfe body, another time it is the firſt fruits of the bread to come: otherwhile fleſh: at another time ſpirit: At laſt, about the end he ſaith, For albeit ſome named the bread and wine patternes of Chriſts body and blood, as that holy man <hi>Baſill;</hi> yet after the ſanctifying they called it not ſo, but before the ſacrifice was ſanctified. But in that which is commonly called the liturgie of <hi>Baſill,</hi> it is plaine otherwiſe, and the reſt of the Fathers do oftentimes the like. And <hi>Damaſcenus</hi> himſelfe ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vp his oration with this concluſion: And they be called the patterns of things to come, not becauſe they be not verely the bodie and blood of Chriſt, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe now by them we be made partakers of the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Chriſt, and then ſhall be by vnderſtanding, by ſight onely. What ſhall we do with this man, who a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before denied that they were called patternes after ſanctification, and now he himſelfe doeth plainely call them patternes after ſanctification? what maner incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie is this? This is not a teaching of myſteries, but in ſaying ſomewhile one thing, and another while an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, it is to wrap all things in blind darkeneſſe. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I thinke in my mind, that <hi>Damaſcenus</hi> knew not how to determine this matter certainely, but did heape to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether haſtily and confuſedly thoſe things which hee had read, and which were written wiſely of the olde Fathers, and when hee could not winde himſelfe out, hee floteth to and fro, and as the Grecians terme it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is to ſay, wafteth with his wings. For that hee was perſwaded that there ſhould be a carnall (as they terme it) tranſubſtantiation, that is not likely, ſince that the very Greeke Church vnto this preſent day hath not admitted that opinion. And indeede no
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1338:33"/>
marueile, if in this myſterie he ſaw the leſſe, or had no ſound opinion, if thoſe things be true which be repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of him in his life, that after hee was made a Monke hee fondly became a basketſeller in the market place, that he fained fooliſh miracles, that he was a ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous worſhipper of Images, and a moſt earneſt main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer of the ſame.</p>
            <p>The authoritie of them of old time ought to bee of more credit with vs, whoſe iudgement commended to vs with learning and vnfained godlineſſe, is of much more weight: vvho for the vnderſtanding of this ſo great a myſtery, exclude all ſence of the fleſh, and cal vs backe to a ſpirituall maner of vnderſtanding. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſely and learnedly doth <hi>Bertram,</hi> which was no long time after, ſeeme to haue obſerued this diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the ancient Fathers, and agreeable alſo to the ſcriptures, and to haue ſet foorth in a worke of his, though not long, yet clearely and truely, what ought to be thought of this controuerſie: and if wee gather thereout a few places fit for our purpoſe, it ſhall not be amiſſe; for he is neither a very new Author, ſeeing hee liued about ſeuen hundreth yeeres paſt, and beſide, he was no leſſe famous for his life then for his learning. With many arguments hee proueth this propoſition, That the fleſh of Chriſt taken of the Virgine, and that which is taken in the ſacrament, differ one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For he writeth in this maner, expounding theſe wordes of <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> That is the vndoubtedly true fleſh of Chriſt, that was crucified, that was buried. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is verely a ſacrament of that fleſh. The Lorde Ieſus himſelfe cryeth,<note place="margin">Bertramus de corp. &amp; ſang. Chriſti.</note> 
               <hi>This is my body.</hi> How diligently, ſaith <hi>Bertram,</hi> hovv wiſely is this diſtinction made? Of the fleſh of Chriſt vvhich was crucified, which was buried, that is, by the vvhich Chriſt vvas both cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1338:33"/>
and buried, he ſaith, It is his very fleſh indeed: but of that which is receiued in the ſacrament, he ſaith, It is therefore verily the ſacrament of that fleſh: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a diſtinction betweene the ſacrament of his fleſh, and the trueth of his fleſh, in that he ſaid, That in the trueth of his fleſh which he tooke of the Virgine, he was both crucified and buried, and therefore ſaid that the myſterie that is now miniſtred in the Church, is verily a ſacrament of that fleſh wherein he was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: manifeſtly inſtructing the faithfull, that that fleſh in which Chriſt was crucified and buried, is not a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, but the trueth of nature. But this fleſh which now conteineth in a myſterie the ſimilitude of that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is not fleſh in forme, but in Sacrament: ſo that in forme it is bread, in ſacrament the true body of Chriſt, as the Lord IESVS himſelfe crieth, <hi>This is my body.</hi> Whoſe minde that we may the better vnderſtand, it is to be marked (the which we did alſo note before) that as he meaneth the body of Chriſt two maner of wayes, ſo doth he alledge alſo two maner of truethes of the ſame, namely the one trueth properly, which he ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the trueth in forme, and the trueth of nature, which he doth attribute to the fleſh that was crucified and buried; the other a ſpirituall trueth, which he ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the true body in the ſacrament.</p>
            <p>The ſame man repeating the ſaying of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> The food then is not corporall but ſpirituall, ſaith: Thou mayeſt not therefore bring the ſenſe of the fleſh: for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that, there is nothing here determined. It is indeed the body of Chriſt, but not corporall, but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall: It is the blood of Chriſt, but not corporall, but ſpirituall. There is nothing therefore to be vnderſtood corporally, but ſpiritually. It is the body of Chriſt, but not corporally: and it is the blood of Chriſt, but
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1338:34"/>
not corporally. Note when he ſaith, Not corporally, he meaneth not properly corporally, (for by the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall eating alſo in the ſacrament we are corporally an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed with Chriſt, as <hi>Cyrillus</hi> and <hi>Hilarius</hi> doe witnes,) but myſtically, not properly. The ſame man ſaith of the ſame <hi>Ambroſe</hi> a little after: He hath taught vs very plainely, how we ought to vnderſtand the myſterie of the Body and Blood of Chriſt. For after he had ſaid that our Fathers did eate ſpiritual food, and drinke ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall drinke, when as for all that there is no man that doubteth, but the <hi>Manna</hi> which they did eate, and the water which they did drinke, were corporall; he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth it to the myſterie which now is miniſtred in the Church, defining after what ſort it is the body of Chriſt. For in that he ſaith, The body of God is a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall body, Chriſt vndoubtedly is God, and that body vvhich he tooke of the Virgine <hi>Mary,</hi> which ſuffered, which was buried, which roſe againe, was vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a true body, the ſame that continued viſible, and able to be felt: but that body which is called the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of God, is not corporall but ſpirituall. But if it be ſpirituall, then is it not viſible, nor able to be felt: and therefore <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> addeth, ſaying, The body of Chriſt is the body of a diuine Spirit. But a diuine ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is nothing that is corporall, nothing that is corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, nothing able to be felt. But this body which is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnized in the Church, as touching the viſible forme, is both corruptible and to be felt. Soone after alſo he concludeth vpon the words of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> in this wiſe: By the authoritie of this great learned man, we be well taught, that there is a great difference betweene the body wherein Chriſt ſuffered, and the blood which he ſhed hanging vpon the Croſſe out of his ſide, and this body which in the myſterie of Chriſtes paſsion is daily
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1338:34"/>
ſolemnized of the faithfull, and that blood alſo which is receiued in the mouth of the faithfull, is a myſterie of that blood wherwith the whole world was redeemed. Hee confirmeth that alſo by the authoritie of <hi>Hierom,</hi> and after rehearſall of this place, The blood and fleſh of Chriſt is vnderſtood two maner of wayes; either that ſpirituall, &amp;c. thus he concludeth: With no ſmall difference hath this doctour made a diſtinction of the body and blood of Chriſt. For in that he ſaith, that the fleſh or blood which are daily receiued of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full are ſpirituall, and yet that the fleſh that was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and the blood which was ſhed with the ſouldiers ſpeare, are not ſaid to be ſpirituall nor diuine; he doeth manifeſtly ſignifie, that they differ as much one from another, as do ſpirituall things and corporall, viſible and inuiſible, diuine and humane, and that thoſe things which differ from themſelues, are not all one. But the ſpirituall fleſh which is receiued in the mouth of the faithfull, and the ſpirituall blood which is daily giuen to the faithfull to drinke, doe differ from the fleſh that was crucified, and from the blood that was ſhed with the ſouldiers ſpeare, as the authoritie of this man doth witneſſe. Therefore they be not all one: For that fleſh which was crucified, was made of the fleſh of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, framed together of bones and ſinevves, and ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the features of the members of a man, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the ſpirit, of a reaſonable ſoule, indued with reaſon into a life proper to it ſelfe, and motions agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the ſame. But on the other ſide, the ſpirituall fleſh which feedeth ſpiritually the people that doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, after the forme that it beareth outwardly, is made of the graines of corne, by the handes of the workeman, framed together of no ſinewes and bones, ſeuered with no varietie of members, quickened with
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1338:35"/>
no reaſonable ſubſtance, nor can exerciſe any proper motions. For whatſoeuer giueth the ſubſtance of life, it is of a ſpirituall force, and of an inuiſible working, and of a diuine power. Againe, of the wordes of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> he concludeth in this maner: By authoritie of this doctour intreating of the Lords wordes of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his body &amp; blood we be manifeſtly taught, that thoſe wordes of the Lord be to be vnderſtood ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, and not carnally, as hee himſelfe ſayeth, <hi>The words which I ſpeake to you, bee ſpirit and life,</hi> Namely the words of eating his fleſh and drinking his blood: for he ſpake it vpon that occaſion, whereat his diſciples were offended. Therefore that they ſhould not bee offended, the heauenly Maſter calleth them back from the fleſh to the Spirit, and from a corporall ſight to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible vnderſtanding. We ſee therefore the food of the Lords body, and the drinke of his blood, are after a ſort his very body, and his very blood, namely in that they be Spirit and life. Hee addeth againe after the matter proued: Therefore we ſee, that there is a great difference betweene the myſterie of the body &amp; blood of Chriſt which is now receiued of the faithfull in the Congregation, and that body which was borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which ſuffered, which was buried, which roſe againe, which aſcended into heauen, which ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the right hand of the Father. For this that is miniſtred in the way, is to be taken ſpiritually: For Faith beleeueth that which it ſeeth not, and ſpiritually feedeth the ſoule, and doth reioyce the heart, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth euerlaſting life, and incorruption, while that is not minded which feedeth the body, which is cruſhed with teeth, which is broken in pieces, but that which by faith is ſpiritually receiued. But that body where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſt ſuffered and roſe againe, is his owne proper
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1338:35"/>
body taken of the Virgin <hi>Maries</hi> body, able to be felt and ſeene, euen after his reſurrection, as he himſelfe ſaid to his diſciples, <hi>Beholde my hands and my feet: for I am euen he, handle me and ſee, for a ſpirit hath not fleſh and bones, as ye ſee me haue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bertram</hi> writeth many things to this purpoſe: but let it ſuffice that wee haue touched thus much. Which mans expoſition, and manner of diſputing vpon the Sacrament, is (in mine opinion) diligently to be way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and imbraced, for tvvo reſpects: Firſt, becauſe hee ſticketh to the authoritie and teſtimonie not onely of thoſe fathers of whom he hath repeated a few, but alſo many moe, I might ſay of all the moſt auncient: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily, becauſe that where the credit of the man was ſo much that he was prouoked to write by a moſt famous Prince, and his writing publiſhed abroad, and in ſight of all men, he was praiſed of many, reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of none, or noted of any one ſpot of erronious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, whereby it came to paſſe that before theſe new groſſe and naturall tranſubſtantiation makers ſprung vp, the doctrine of <hi>Bertram</hi> touching the Sacrament, was allovved by the iudgement of euery man that was beſt learned: Albeit this terme of tranſubſtantiation being indeed new &amp; not neceſſarie, yet perhaps might haue ſome place, as the word Tranſ-elementation, if they had not brought in another change of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances then a ſacramentall, and that which the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fathers did vnderſtand, which is brought to paſſe the former ſubſtance remayning ſtill. But they not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the noueltie of the terme, haue inuented a monſtrous interpretation. For they appoint the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry proper body of Chriſt to be in the Sacrament, and plucke from it the true properties of a mans body, whereas it ſhould ſeeme that <hi>Aquinas</hi> himſelfe was not
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1338:36"/>
ignorant of the diſtinction aboue mentioned.<note place="margin">Aquin. <hi>3.</hi> parte. Sum. q. <hi>76.</hi> art. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> For he writeth <hi>3. part. Sum. q. 76. art 3.</hi> on this manner: Chriſt is whole vnder ech peece of the formes of Bread and Wine, not onely when the hoſte is broken, but alſo when it remaineth whole: neyther is there diſtance of parts one from another, as the eye from the eye, or the eye from the eare, or the head from the feete, as there is in other bodies organicall: for ſuch maner of diſtance is in the true body of Chriſt, but not as it is in this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. He affirmeth the true body of Chriſt to bee one, which is organicall, and hath difference of mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, which alſo hee denyeth to bee in the Sacrament; and that to be another, which is in the Sacrament, and wanteth varietie of members: which thing if he meant of the ſpirituall body as the old writers did ſpeake, he iudged right; but if hee meant to ſignifie any maſſe of fleſh without forme, it is a great abſurditie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the opinion of all the old writers.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lombardus.</note>
               <hi>Lombardus</hi> alſo Author of the ſentences, concerning the verie and proper fleſh of Chriſt <hi>lib 3. Sentent. Diſt. 3.</hi> ſaith thus: Chriſts fleſh that was taken, is neither hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, nor of the aire, nor of any other nature then of ſuch as all mens fleſh is. Since therefore the manner and nature of the fleſh of Chriſt is common with the fleſh of other men, as <hi>Lombardus</hi> ſaith, and ſuch fleſh as <hi>Aquinas</hi> affirmeth commeth not into the Sacrament; it followeth by their teſtimonie, that theſe two kindes of fleſh differ much. And that this may the better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, and bee laide vp in memorie, I thought it not without profit to adde, of ſuch things as we haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of before, a certaine diſtinction which the Greekes call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by compariſon.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The proper bodie of Chriſt, hath the naturall forme of a mans body: The myſticall bodie hath not.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:1338:36"/>2 The proper body hath a head, breaſt, members ſeuered: The myſticall hath not.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The proper body hath bones, vaines, &amp; ſinewes: The myſtical hath not.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That may bee ſeene and touched: This can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be ſeene nor touched.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That is indued with the true ſences of a body: This is without ſence, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſaith.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That is organicall: This is not.</p>
            <p n="7">7 That is no figure: This is a figure of his proper body.</p>
            <p n="8">8 That is not in myſterie: This is in myſterie.</p>
            <p n="9">9 That, of his owne nature, is humane and bodily: This is heauenly, diuine, and ſpirituall.</p>
            <p n="10">10 The matter of that is not ſubiect to corruption: The materiall part of this is bread, and is corrupted.</p>
            <p n="11">11 No man may eate that by it ſelfe: This, both a man may and ought to eate.</p>
            <p n="12">12 That is contained in one place: This, whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the Sacrament is miniſtred, is preſent; but not as in a place.</p>
            <p n="13">13 That is not a Sacrament of another body: This is a Sacrament of another body.</p>
            <p n="14">14 That being taken of the virgin <hi>Maries</hi> bodie, was once create: This is not taken of the Virgin, but daylie by the myſticall benediction is create potential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, by the teſtimonie of <hi>Auguſtin</hi> and <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15 That is a naturall body: This is aboue nature.</p>
            <p n="16">16 Finally, that is ſimply: This is after a ſort.</p>
            <p n="17">17 That properly &amp; perfectly: This is a bodie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly.</p>
            <p>Hitherto wee haue ſpoken of the difference which the auncient Fathers haue godly and diligently obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, betweene Chriſts proper bodie, and the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1338:37"/>
of the ſame bodie. In the which although many things haue beene ſpoken, which doe not only declare that there is a difference (which in this place we meant to doe) but alſo doe admoniſh vs vvithall, what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of bodie that is in the ſacrament: Yet becauſe wee haue not hitherto ſo fully expreſſed this point, as the weightines of the matter requireth, We haue thought good from hence-forvvard to intreate of this part more fullie; Namely, in vvhat ſort this Sacrament is the Lords bodie, and wherefore our Lord himſelfe at the firſt, as the Euangeliſts make mention, aftervvard <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle, laſtly all they of old time, following the authoritie of them, haue left in writing that it is ſo called, and is ſo indeed; not that this manner which is a ſpirituall and hid thing, can be found out by mans reaſon, or that wee goe about to ſearch out curiouſly ſuch things as bee forbidden and denyed, but that all mans inuentions ſet apart, we may follow thoſe things that haue bene left vs by the authoritie of Scriptures, and auncient Fathers that agree with them, and that manner which the Lord himſelfe would wee ſhould know, and the Church inſtructed by him and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, hath receiued, not to depart from that. This is to bee holden faſt which wee proued before, that not onely the Lordes wordes, which be ſpoken in the 6. Chapter of <hi>Iohn, Vnleſſe yee eate the fleſh &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>My fleſh is verily meate,</hi> and the reſt that followeth in the ſame place, but alſo theſe wordes of the Lords ſupper, <hi>Take ye, eate ye, this is my body,</hi> and <hi>This is my blood,</hi> are to bee vnderſtood ſpiritually, not carnally, and that one maner of eating is meant in both places. When I ſay, Not carnally, I meane, Not according to the letter, nor as the words doe properly ſound: for this is to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand carnally, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> witneſſeth vpon <hi>Iohn,</hi> of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1338:37"/>
theſe words, <hi>The fleſh profiteth nothing.</hi> What is it,<note place="margin">Chryſostom. in Ioan. Hom. <hi>46.</hi>
               </note> ſaith he, to vnderſtand carnally? To vnderſtand the things ſimply as they be ſpoken, and nothing elſe. For thoſe things that be ſeene, are not ſo to be iudged, but all my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries are to be conſidered with inward eyes, that is to ſay, ſpiritually. Let not this rule of <hi>Chryſostome</hi> go out of our minds. But theſe two, Carnally, and Spiritually, are contrary; when the one is forbidden, the other is commanded, and contrarywiſe. And that carnall ſenſe hath no place in this myſterie, not onely <hi>Chryſostome</hi> is the Author, as we recited euen now, and <hi>Cyprian,</hi> where he ſaith, Neither doth carnall ſenſe pearſe the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of ſo great a depth, and <hi>Theophylactus</hi> writing thus, But becauſe we vnderſtand it ſpiritually, we be neither deuourers of fleſh, and yet be ſanctified by that meat. But to be ſhort, I may in maner ſay, that all the ancient Fathers with one voice do forbid vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the wordes of the Lords Supper carnally, and command a ſpirituall meaning: The which by many teſtimonies repeated in this peece of worke, euery man may readily perceiue. Neither is this ſufficient, if we auoyd one maner of vnderſtanding carnally, and fall into another. For he that doth vnderſtand the eating of Chriſts fleſh after the letter, and as it were a proper kinde of ſpeech, he is a carnall <hi>Capernaite,</hi> whether he ſuppoſe it to be done properly one way or another. That is plaine by theſe wordes of <hi>Augustin</hi> vpon the 98. Pſalme:<note place="margin">Augustine in Pſal. <hi>98.</hi>
               </note> It ſeemed a hard matter to them that he ſaid, <hi>Vnleſſe a man eate, &amp;c.</hi> They tooke it fondly, and imagined of it carnally, and thought that the Lord would haue cut out peeces of his body, and haue giuen to them. And a little after: That which I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, vnderſtand ye ſpiritually. You ſhall not eate this body which you ſee, I haue commended to you a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1338:38"/>
ſacrament, if it be ſpiritually vnderſtood, it will giue you life. Here <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calleth carnall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding fooliſhneſſe, and appointeth ſpirituall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding as neceſſary. And his meaning is not that this is onely a carnall ſenſe, if a man ſhould imagine of the cut pieces of the Lords body, albeit he rehearſeth but this one carnall way of vnderſtanding, but alſo of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the like. For it is a likely matter, that euen all the <hi>Capernaites</hi> did vnderſtand it carnally, and yet not all after one way.<note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> For one maner is rehearſed of <hi>Cyprian</hi> writing thus: It ſeemed to them a horrible and wicked matter to feed of the fleſh of man, imagining that this had bene ſo ſpoken, as though they ſhould haue bene taught to eate his fleſh either ſodden, or roſted, or cut in gobbets.<note place="margin">Cyrillus.</note> And <hi>Cyrillus</hi> doth impute to them another kinde of carnall vnderſtanding: for he ſaith, For after they had heard, <hi>Verily verily I ſay to you, vnleſſe ye eate the fleſh, &amp;c.</hi> they thought Chriſt had called them to the cruel maner of wilde beaſts, and that they were prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to an appetite to eate the raw fleſh of man, and drinke blood, which things bee horrible euen to bee heard. Wherefore if we beleeue that the fleſh of Chriſt properly ſo called is there preſent, whether we thinke it raw, roſt, or ſodden, either whole or cut in gobbets, open or couert, the ſenſe is vtterly carnal, &amp; the words be carnally vnderſtood. For it is not therefore to be thought a ſpirituall ſenſe, becauſe they ſay the fleſh of Chriſt is preſent inuiſibly: For if their meaning be of the proper fleſh, we cannot ſay that we eate him not therefore carnally, becauſe we ſee him not. The blinde ſee not thoſe things which they eate, and men many times in pottage and brothes eate egges and fleſh, which neither they ſee, nor otherwhile feele in taſte. But none of all theſe is a ſpirituall ſenſe, or doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1338:38"/>
a more hie meaning, but as the wordes ſimply do ſignifie, eate egges and fleſh, which <hi>Chryſostome</hi> termeth carnall vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>Since therefore, all carnall meaning of the words ſet apart, a ſpirituall muſt be had and retained therein; we ought godly to ſeeke, and reuerently to ſearch out, what maner of vnderſtanding that is, that hath bene ſet foorth and commended vnto vs; the which we alſo wil indeauour our ſelues to doe, not departing from the footſteps of the very ſame Fathers. Euen as there be two parts, whereof the ſacrament doth conſiſt, that is, the outward ſigne, and inward vertue: ſo is that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſenſe which is here required, taken of both theſe parts. The carnall vnderſtanding doth follow the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> when he had heard, <hi>Vnleſse a man bee borne againe of water and the ſpirit, &amp;c.</hi> hee asketh this queſtion: <hi>How can a man be borne againe? Can he returne againe into his mothers wombe?</hi> The ſpirituall man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth from the letter, and ſo are we borne againe in Baptiſme. And the waſhing is of two ſorts: Outward and inward; carnall and ſpiritual: the one according to the letter, and is made by water; the other doth ſhunne the letter, and is performed in ſpirit. Either of them is ſaid to be truely done, but after a diuers maner. The firſt maner of ſpeaking is proper, the other figuratiue; and the figure hath otherwhile relation to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſimilitude, otherwhile to the vertue inwardly hid. It is figuratiuely ſpoken, <hi>All fleſh is graſse.</hi> For the withering graſſe hath a certaine ſimilitude of a man that ſoone periſheth. <hi>Beware of the leauen of the Phariſes.</hi> This is taken of the proper ſtrength of leauen, which ſpreadeth the taſte therof thorowout the whole lumpe; very like whereunto is the infection of ill doctrine. Now in this ſacrament the Fathers of old time haue
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1338:39"/>
noted tvvo things, for either of the which it may well be called and accompted the body of Chriſt, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when it comprehendeth them both. For both becauſe the Bread is a figure of the true bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, it is iuſtly called his body, and much more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath the liuely force of the ſame ioyned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but in eſpeciall, becauſe it comprehendeth both. And that the figure of any thing hath by good reaſon the name of the ſame, and is called the thing it ſelfe, indeed <hi>Eſay</hi> ſheweth where he ſaith, <hi>The people bee ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily hay,</hi> and <hi>He verily hath borne our iniquities.</hi> By a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude is the people called hay, and the Lord vpon the Croſſe had in him a ſimilitude of a ſinnefull man, although he himſelfe was without ſinne: after which maner alſo Chriſt is ſaid to be the true Vine. <hi>I am the true Vine,</hi> ſaith he: and other places which a man ſhall often finde in the Scriptures. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> ſpake the trueth when he ſaid, <hi>Behold the Lambe of God.</hi> The Lord himſelfe ſaid the trueth when he ſaid of <hi>Nathaniel, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold an Iſraelite in deed in whom is no deceit.</hi> That word Verily, or Indeed, is not to be referred to the outward, but to the inward circumciſion: for the people of God alſo vvhich is gathered of the Gentiles is now more truely called Iſrael, then the Ievves themſelues, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſaying of <hi>Paul, We be the Circumciſion which worſhip God in ſpirit.</hi> And this, <hi>He is not a Iew which in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance is a Iew, but he is a Iew which is a Iew in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret.</hi> Yet be we not for all that properly Iewes, but we are called ſo by a figure, &amp; all theſe figuratiue ſpeaches for the outward ſimilitude of the things. Wherefore it ought to ſeeme neither a new thing, nor yet a marueile, if the Lords bread be ſaid to be verily the body, where it is a figure of the body.<note place="margin">August. ad Bonif. epist. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Hereupon <hi>Augustin</hi> to <hi>Boniface</hi> in his 23. Epiſtle ſaith:
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1338:39"/>
For thus wee ſpeake oftentimes: As when Eaſter is at hand, we ſay, The Lords paſsion ſhal be to morrow, or the next day, where hee ſuffered ſo many yeeres agoe, and that paſsion hath neuer been done but once. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe vpon the very Eaſter day wee ſay, To day the Lord roſe againe, when ſince hee roſe againe ſo many yeeres are paſt. Why is none ſo fooliſh to reproue vs, and ſay we lie in ſo ſaying, But becauſe wee vſe to call theſe dayes according to the ſimilitude of them in which theſe thinges were done? So that it is called the ſame day which is not the ſame, but by courſe of time is like vnto it, and it is ſaid to be done that day for the miniſtring of the Sacrament, which was not done that day but long agoe. Was not Chriſt once offered in himſelfe? yet in the Sacrament, not onely in all the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities of Eaſter, but euery day hee is offered to the people. Againe he lieth not, that being asked the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, doth anſwere that he is offered: for if the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhould not haue a certaine likeneſſe of thoſe things whereof they be Sacraments, they ſhould be no Sacraments at all: and of this likenes alſo many times they take the names of the things themſelues. Euen as therfore after a certaine manner, the Sacrament of the bodie of Chriſt is the bodie of Chriſt, and the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the blood of Chriſt is the blood of Chriſt: ſo alſo the Sacrament of faith is faith. By this place of <hi>Augustin,</hi> and many other both of his &amp; other fathers, we ſee that the figures and ſimilitudes of things bee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten called by the name of the thinges themſelues, and that this is one cauſe, though not the onely, why this ſacrament is called verily Chriſts bodie.</p>
            <p>To this agree thoſe things that we commonly finde amongſt olde writers, who tearme this Sacrament o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhile a figure, as <hi>Tertull. cont. Mart. lib. 4.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull.</note> 
               <hi>This is my
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1338:40"/>
body,</hi> ſaith he, that is to ſay, a figure of my bodie. And <hi>Nazianzene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nazianzene.</note> which ſaid the old Paſſouer was a figure of a figure.<note place="margin">Auguſtin.</note> And <hi>Augustin,</hi> The bodie, ſaith hee, of Chriſt is the trueth, and a figure. Sometime a ſigne, as <hi>Auguſtin contra Adimant cap. 12.</hi> The Lord put no doubt to ſay, <hi>This is my body,</hi> when he gaue the ſigne of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.<note place="margin">Chriſostome.</note> And <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vpon the 26. of Matthew <hi>Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia 83.</hi> For if Chriſt be not dead, whoſe figure &amp; ſigne is this ſacrifice? Finallie, of ſome it is called a figure, and a badge, as of <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtom;</hi> of ſome other, an example, patterne, and image, as of <hi>Ambroſe, Baſill,</hi> and <hi>Origen:</hi> wherefore not without cauſe, it hath alſo the name of that thing, whoſe figure, badge, and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne it is. Wherefore it is the more to be maruelled what commeth into their mindes, that cannot abide to haue it called a figure, nor doe acknowledge any fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure in the words of the Supper, but doe reprochfully call them that doe acknowledge it, figure framers: whereas it is plaine for all that, that all old writers did ſo call it, and that by thoſe words of the Lords ſupper, the Lorde did conſecrate the Sacrament of his body: this being manifeſt alſo, that after the letter &amp; proper manner of ſpeech, the bodie of Chriſt ſignifieth one thing, and the Sacrament of his bodie another. And if it ſhall not be a figure, it ſhall neither be a ſigne nor a ſacrament, And ſo ſuch as be ready to call other men ſacramentaries, they themſelues doe take away the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments altogether. Therefore let no man doubt but this ſacrament is both a figure, and therefore doeth alſo take the name of that thing whereof it is a figure.</p>
            <p>We ſaid there was another thing which the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers acknowledging in this ſacrament, would haue it verily to be the Lords body, and that is the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the body it ſelfe that is of force, and giueth life,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1338:40"/>
which vertue by grace and myſticall bleſsing is ioyned with the Bread and Wine, and is called by ſundry names, where the matter it ſelfe is all one. Of <hi>Auguſtin</hi> an intelligible, inuiſible &amp; ſpirituall body: Of <hi>Hierom,</hi> diuine &amp; ſpirituall fleſh: Of <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> a heauenly thing: Of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> a ſpirituall foode, and body of a diuine ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: Of other, ſome ſuch like thing. And this alſo doth make much the more, that the ſacrament is moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to haue the name of the true body and blood, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not onely outvvardly it ſhoweth forth a figure and image of it, but alſo inwardly it draweth with it a hid and ſecret naturall propertie of the ſame bodie, that is to ſay, a vertue that giueth life: ſo that it cannot now be thought a vaine figure, or the ſigne of a thing cleane abſent, but the very body of the Lord, diuine indeede and ſpirituall, but preſent in grace, full of vertue, migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in operation. And it hapneth often, that the names of the thinges themſelues be giuen to their vertue and ſtrength. We ſay leauen is in the whole lumpe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as a ſmall quantitie of leauen cannot ſpread ſo farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, but the ſtrength and ſharpenes of the leauen. We ſay that the fire doth warme vs, when the heate of the fire doth it, we being a good way off from the fire. Likewiſe that the Sunne is preſent, doth lighten, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, nouriſheth, when indeede the heat of the Sunne doth it, and the Sunne himſelfe cannot goe out of his ſpheare. So is a King ſaid to be in all his realme, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the power of his dominon. Neither doth the ſcripture want theſe examples: for we often meet with them. Wee will at this time bee content with one of them, but very manifeſt. Chriſt ſpake of Iohn, ſaying, <hi>He is Helias,</hi> becauſe he was indewed with the vertue or power of <hi>Helias,</hi> the angell vnto <hi>Zacharie</hi> witneſsing the ſame and ſaying, <hi>Hee ſhall goe before him in the ſpirit
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1338:41"/>
and power of Helias.</hi> Likewiſe therefore as <hi>Iohn</hi> was <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias,</hi> becauſe he had the ſpirit and power of <hi>Helias;</hi> So the Lords bread is the body of Chriſt, becauſe it hath his grace and liuely power ioyned therewithall.</p>
            <p>But that this is not a fained or a lately ſprung opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but was receiued, and allowed of the auncient wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, we wil confirme it by their open teſtimonies, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reciting ſome of the forenamed places, and partly adding other. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> vpon <hi>Iohn tract. 27. If therefore yee ſhall ſee the Sonne of man where hee was before:</hi> What meaneth this? by this hee anſwereth that which had troubled them: by this he openeth the cauſe why they were offended: by this plainely, if they would vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. For they thought that hee would haue giuen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them his body: but he ſaid that he would aſcend into heauen euen whole. When ye ſhall ſee the ſonne of man aſcend where hee was before, ſurely euen then ſhall ye ſee, that hee giueth not his body in ſuch ſort as ye imagine; ſurely euen then ſhall yee vnderſtand that his grace is not conſumed by biting, nor periſheth by eating. The ſame man out of the ſermon of the words of the Lord, and it is rehearſed <hi>de conſecrat. Diſt. 2.</hi> The faithfull doe know how they do eat the fleſh of Chriſt: Euery man taketh his part, whereupon the parts bee called the grace it ſelfe: by parts hee is eaten, and he remayneth all whole: by parts he is eaten in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and remayneth all whole in thy heart. The ſame man vpon <hi>Iohn, tract. 50.</hi> Thou haſt Chriſt both at this preſent, and in time to come; preſently by ſigne, preſently by the ſacrament of Baptiſme, preſently by the meate and drinke of the Altar. Thou haſt Chriſt preſently, but thou ſhalt haue him alway: for when thou ſhalt goe from hence, thou ſhalt come to him that ſaid to the thiefe, <hi>This day ſhalt thou be with mee in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:1338:41"/>
And ſoone after: <hi>The poore ſhall yee alway haue with you, but mee ſhall yee not alwayes haue.</hi> Let good men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this alſo, and not be troubled: for he ſpake of the preſence of his body. For according to his maieſtie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his prouidence, according to his vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and inuiſible grace, that is fulfilled which he hath ſpoken, <hi>Behold I am with you daily, euen vnto the end of the world.</hi> But according to the fleſh which the Worde tooke vpon him, according to that that hee was borne of the Virgin, according to that that hee was taken of the Iewes, that he was faſtned to the tree, that hee was taken downe from the Croſſe, that he was wrapped in linnen clothes, that he was laid in the graue, that hee appeared in his reſurrection, yee ſhall not haue him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies with you. Why? Becauſe according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his body he was conuerſant with his Diſciples fortie dayes, and they being in his company, and ſeeing him, and not following him, he aſcended into heauen, and is not here: for he is there, hee ſitteth on the right hand of the Father. Theſe be <hi>Auguſtins</hi> words. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he ſaid before that Chriſt is preſent with vs by faith, and by the ſacraments; afterward he ſaid that he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with vs by Maieſtie, by vnſpeakeable and inuiſible grace, and ſo that is fulfilled by him which hee ſpake, <hi>Behold I am with you to &amp;c.</hi> But according to the proper preſence of the fleſh, that he is not here, which proper nature of the fleſh alſo he hath dilated plentifully by a <hi>Periphraſis,</hi> to exclude altogether ſuch a manner of preſence, &amp; to eſtabliſh his preſence in the ſacraments by grace &amp; power. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> teacheth vs by the Lords words, that his true and proper body is aſcended into heauen euen whole, but the grace of that body we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by the ſacraments, which is neither conſumed by biting, nor periſhed by eating.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:1338:42"/>
               <note place="margin">Idem in Pſal. <hi>65.</hi>
               </note>To this agreeth that the ſame Author writeth vpon the 65. Pſal. The murtherers dranke the ſame blood by grace,<note place="margin">Idem in Ioan. tract. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> which they ſhed through madnes. The ſame man vpon the Goſpel of <hi>Iohn tract 26.</hi> Giue eare to the Apoſtle: <hi>I would not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>haue you ignorant, brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, that our Fathers were all vnder a cloud, and all did eate one maner ſpirituall food:</hi> Spirituall truely all one, but corporall, another: for they did eate <hi>Manna,</hi> we ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, but the ſame ſpirituall meat that wee doe. And they all dranke the ſame ſpiritual drinke: yet they one thing, we another in outward appearance, which notwithſtanding did ſignifie all one in ſpiritual power. He calleth the ſacrament ſpirituall food, for the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall power ioyned therewith, which power alſo was in the ſacraments of the old teſtament, albeit our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſignes and theirs were diuerſe. The ſpiritual po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer was all one in both: That of a body to bee borne at his time; This of a body alreadie borne, ſuffered and rayſed againe. So <hi>Manna</hi> was to them the bodie of Chriſt, as the ſacrament of thankeſ-giuing is now to vs. For this ſpirituall power, <hi>Auguſtin</hi> alſo called it, as we ſaid before, a ſpirituall, inuiſible, and intelligible body, wherby is ſignified the viſible body of the Lord, and able to be felt. Hereunto alſo belongeth that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame Author: The body of Chriſt is both trueth, and a figure: Trueth, while the body &amp; blood of Chriſt, by the power of the holy Ghoſt, in power of the ſame is made of the ſubſtance of bread &amp; wine: but a figure is that which is outwardly ſeene. The meaning of theſe words be, that the ſubſtance of bread &amp; wine be made the body of Chriſt, for the power of his body giuen to them by the holy Ghoſt. The ſame man in <hi>Pſalme 77.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem in Pſal. <hi>77.</hi>
               </note> Their meate and drinke therefore in my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie was all one with ours; yet in ſignification, not in
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:1338:42"/>
outward appearance: for the ſelfe ſame Chriſt was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured to them in the rocke, but to vs he was made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in fleſh. But hee ſaith, That <hi>God was not well pleaſed with them all.</hi> In that he ſaith, <hi>not with all,</hi> there were ſome then there in whom God was pleaſed. And albeit the ſacraments were common to all, yet his grace, which is the power of the ſacraments, was not common to all. This place of <hi>Auguſtin</hi> if it bee well weighed, doth much helpe to vnderſtand how Chriſt is preſent in the ſacraments. For he ioyneth together theſe two, Signification and Grace, which hee affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be the ſtrength of the ſacrament.</p>
            <p>To theſe agree thoſe things which <hi>Ambroſe</hi> writeth <hi>lib. 6. de Sacramentis:</hi> Afterward,<note place="margin">Ambroſ. de Sacra. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> when the Diſciples of Chriſt could not away with his talke, but hearing that hee would giue them his fleſh to eate, and his blood to drinke, went their way; yet <hi>Peter</hi> alone ſaid, <hi>Thou haſt the words of eternall life, whither ſhall I goe from thee?</hi> Leaſt therfore any moe ſhould ſo ſay, as though there ſhould be a kind of loathſomenes of blood, but that the grace of redemption might remaine, thou therefore takeſt the ſacrament in a ſimilitude, but thou doeſt obtaine the grace and vertue of his true nature. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> doth plainely teach, how it is true fleſh. For hee hath noted both: The figure, where hee ſaith, thou takeſt it in a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude; and the inward ſtrength, becauſe vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it giueth the grace and vertue of the true nature. Which place being diligentlie marked, the reſidue which be found of his, may eaſilie be expounded. The ſame man in his booke <hi>De ijs qui initiantur myſterijs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem de ijs qui initiantur my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterijs.</note> Chriſt is in that ſacrament, becauſe it is the bodie of Chriſt. Therefore it is not a corporall, but a ſpirituall food: whereupon the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of the figure of it, that our fathers haue eaten ſpirituall meate, &amp; haue
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1338:43"/>
drunke ſpirituall drinke; For the body of God is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall body. The body of Chriſt is the body of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſpirit. By theſe words of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> we be admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, what manner of body this is, and why it is ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, becauſe it hath the ſpirituall vertue of the true bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. For theſe termes, Not a corporall but a ſpirituall food, and The body of the heauenly ſpirit, bee moſt aptly applied to the grace and vertue of his true bodie. Which thing alſo <hi>Euſebius Emiſsenus</hi> confirmeth <hi>de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrat. Diſt. 2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſebius Emiſſenus.</note> Seeing hee meant to take from our eyes the body taken of the virgin, and would place it aboue the ſtarres; it was neceſſary, that in the day of his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the ſacrament of his body &amp; blood ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated vnto vs, to the end that that might bee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped continually in myſterie, which was once offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for a ranſome for vs; that ſeeing a daylie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſing redemption did runne for the ſaluation of all men, it might be a continuall oblation of redemption, and that continuall ſacrifice might liue in memorie, and might euer be preſent in grace, a true, perfect, and only ſacrifice, to be eſteemed in faith, not to be iudged by forme nor outward ſight, but by the inward affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It is manifeſt by the wordes of <hi>Emiſsenus,</hi> that the body that was taken of the Virgin was taken from vs, and was placed aboue the ſtarres, and therefore that the ſacrament of the ſame was neceſſarily ordayned, that that true, perfect, and onely ſacrifice which vvas once offered vpon the Croſſe, might liue continually in memory, and might alvvay be preſent in grace, that vve ſhould not ceaſe to remember continually the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of our perpetuall redemption, neither haue any cauſe vvhy vve ſhould require the preſence of his fleſh, ſeeing vve feele the preſence of the ſame by grace to be of no leſſe efficacie, vvhich is to bee eſteemed by faith,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:1338:43"/>
not to be iudged in forme, or outward appearance, but n the inward affection.<note place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note> And that which he writeth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after in the ſame place: For the inuiſible prieſt doth turne with his word, by a ſecret povver, the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible creatures into the ſubſtance of his body &amp; blood, ſaying thus: <hi>Take ye, eate ye, this is my body &amp;c.</hi> And leaſt we ſhould imagine it a more groſſe ſubſtance, or that called againe which he ſaid before was taken avvay, he alledgeth foorthvvith the example of Regeneration, ſaying, Hovv great benefit therefore the force of the heauenly bleſsing doth worke, and hovv it ought not to be a nevv and vnpoſsible matter to thee, that earthly and mortall things bee changed into the ſubſtance of Chriſt, aske thy ſelfe, that art nevv borne againe in Chriſt. Lately thou waſt farre from life, a ſtranger from mercy, and being invvardly dead, baniſhed from the way of health: and ſuddenly profeſsing the Lawes of Chriſt, and by vvholſome myſteries renued, diddeſt paſſe into the body of the Church, not by ſight, but by beleefe, and of the childe of perdition waſt thought worthy by a ſecret pureneſſe to be made ſonne of God by adoption, abiding ſtil in thy viſible meaſure, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſibly made greater then thy ſelfe, without increaſe of quantitie. For although thou waſt the very ſelfe-ſame man before, yet by augmentation of Faith thou art be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come farre another; in the outvvard man nothing is added, and all is changed in the invvard man, and ſo man was made the Sonne of Chriſt, and Chriſt was formed in the minde of man. Euen as therefore the former baſeneſſe ſet apart, thou haſt ſuddenly put on a nevv dignitie; and as in that God hath healed thoſe things that were amiſſe in thee, put avvay thy imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, vviped avvay thy ſpots, thy eyes are not truſted withall, but thy ſenſes: ſo when thou goeſt vp to the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:1338:44"/>
reuerend Altar to bee fed with the ſpirituall meat, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in thy faith the holy Body and Blood of thy God, honour it, marueile at it, touch it vvith thy minde, take it in the hand of thy heart, and eſpecially receiue it whole, vvith the thirſtie draught of the invvard man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius Emiſſenus</hi> declareth by this ſimilitude, what maner of change is made in the ſacrament; how earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, namely bread and wine, be turned into the ſubſtance of Chriſt, and what maner of ſubſtance that is: ſurely like vnto that change wherewith wee be changed in Baptiſme, and ſuch a ſubſtance as we put on in the waſhing of regeneration, when we paſſe into the body of the Church, where nothing is changed in our outward part, but all in our inward man, which is called a new man and a new creature: and for that cauſe doeth <hi>Emiſſenus</hi> terme this ſubſtance, A ſecret pureneſſe, and new dignitie. In like maner alſo he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the bread of the Lord, which hath gotten a nevv ſubſtance, that is to ſay, a ſecret power and nevv digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Spirituall food, which we behold with faith, touch in minde, take in the handes of our heart, and receiue with the thirſtie draught of our inward man. If it be well and diligently weighed, how <hi>Emiſsenus, Ambroſe,</hi> and the other fathers haue vſed the termes of Nature and Subſtance, it may eaſily be vnderſtood how vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they trouble themſelues, which appoint a carnall ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the fleſh, and doe not apply the wordes to the matter intreated of. For that which we ſee done in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſciplines, that the words do change their ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, according to the matter that euery kinde of learning treateth of, as <hi>Genus, Species, Figura,</hi> and other ſuch like, do ſignifie one thing with the Grammarians, another with the Logitians, and another thing with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther writers; the ſame alſo ought we to obſerue in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1338:44"/>
when they intreat of the Sacraments. The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers make mention of Nature and Subſtance, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, not as naturall Philoſophers ſpeake, but men diſputing of diuine matters, do apply the terme of Nature and Subſtance, to grace, vertue, and efficacie, foraſmuch as the nature of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo requireth.</p>
            <p>The like maner of ſpeaking doeth <hi>Chryſostome</hi> vſe when he ſaith: But that not onely by loue,<note place="margin">Chryſostome.</note> but euen in very deed, we ſhould be turned into that fleſh, that is wrought by the meat which he hath giuen vs. We be turned in very deed into the fleſh of Chriſt: but that conuerſion is ſpirituall, not carnall. And thus much by the way of the ſignification of the words.<note place="margin">Epiphan. in Ancho.</note> 
               <hi>Epiphani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in Anchorato:</hi> For we ſee that our Sauiour tooke into his handes, as the Goſpel containeth, <hi>that hee roſe in the Supper and tooke this, and when he had giuen thankes, he ſaid, This is mine &amp;c.</hi> And we ſee that it is not equall, nor like, neither to the image that is in the fleſh, nor to his inuiſible Godhead, nor to the features of his members. For this is of a round ſhape, and without ſenſe, as farre as pertaineth to power; and therefore his will was to ſpeake by grace, <hi>This is mine &amp;c.</hi> and euery man belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his word: for he that doth not beleeue that he is true as he ſaid, he is fallen from grace and health. But we beleeue that we haue heard, that it is his: for wee know that the Lord is all ſenſe, all indued with ſenſe, all God, all mouing, all working, al light, all incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible, but yet as one which hath giuen vs this with grace. We admoniſhed you before, that <hi>Epiphanius</hi> doth in this place goe about to proue, that man being made after the Image of God, hath verily the Image of God, not according to the proper nature of diuinitie, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grace, and vſeth the ſimilitude taken of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:1338:45"/>
of Thankeſgiuing, the which, according to the proper maner of a body, he denieth to be the body of Chriſt, ſince it hath neither the forme of a true body, neither can feele, or moue, and yet is beleeued by grace to be verily his body.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Idem lib. <hi>3.</hi> cont. Haer. To. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>He is of the ſame opinion <hi>Lib. 3.</hi> againſt <hi>Haereſies To. 2.</hi> where he ſpeaketh thus of the ſacraments: Chriſt went downe into the waters, rather giuing then receiuing, rather offering then needing, giuing them light, making them mighty for a figure of thoſe things that were to be wrought in them; whereby they that beleeue on him in trueth, and haue the faith of trueth, might learne that he was verily made man, and was verily Baptized, and that ſo by his aſcenſion they alſo might come and receiue the vertue of his comming downe, and might be made lightſome by his giuing light, that the ſaying of the Prophet may here bee fulfilled, in the change of power that was giuen for ſaluation, the vertue I meane of the bread that was receiued from <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and of the ſtrength of the water: ſo that here the vertue of the bread and ſtrength of the water may be made of force in Chriſt, that the bread ſhould not be the ſtrength in vs, but the vertue of that bread. And the meat ſurely is bread, but the vertue in it is it that quickneth; And not that water alone ſhould cleanſe vs, but that in the ſtrength of water, by faith and efficacie, and hope, and perfection of myſteries, and calling vpon the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, might be wrought for vs the perfection of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. This place doeth make the other ſomewhat more plaine. There he ſaid, that the bread of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Thankeſgiuing is the body by grace: here he attributeth vertue to the bread, as ſtrength to the water in Baptiſme, often repeating this terme Vertue, and confirming that this vertue and ſtrength doth ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:1338:45"/>
The meat (ſaith he) is bread, but the vertue in it doth quicken: and he declareth that this vertue of the bread doth ſanctifie, and ſtrength of the water is made by grace, not naming it with one word, but deſcribing it more fully with many wordes, ſaying, That theſe things be done by faith, and hope, and the perfection of the myſteries,<note place="margin">Idem in Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cephaleoſi.</note> and calling vpon of the ſanctification for the perfection of ſaluation. The ſame Author re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſeth almoſt the ſame words in <hi>Anacephaleoſis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyprian. de Coena Dom.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame was alſo <hi>Cyprians</hi> opinion. There is giuen (ſaith he) an immortall food differing from common meats, retaining the ſhape of bodily ſubſtance, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing by inuiſible working, that the preſence of a diuine povver is there. Thou heareſt the preſence of a diuine povver, thou heareſt an inuiſible working (that is to ſay) the grace of God. Againe, By the wonted effect of things the weakeneſſe of our faith being aided, is taught by a ſenſible argument, that the effect of eternal life is in the viſible ſacraments. And againe, Euen as in the perſon of Chriſt humanitie was ſeene, and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie hid: ſo into the viſible ſacraments, vnſpeakeably doth the diuine ſubſtance powre it ſelfe. Againe, Theſe words be ſpirit and life, neither doth the carnall ſenſe pearce the vnderſtanding of ſo great a depth, vnleſſe faith be added. The bread is food, the blood is life, the fleſh ſubſtance, the body the Church. A body, for the agreeing of members in one; bread, for the conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of nouriſhment; blood, for the working of quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; fleſh, for the propertie of the humanitie taken. In this place <hi>Cyprian</hi> witneſſeth, that this ſacrament is called fleſh and blood, for the working of the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and for the propertie of the humanitie which Chriſt tooke (that is) the proper vertue thereof, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit and life. And foorthvvith he addeth; Chriſt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:1338:46"/>
doth othervvhile call this ſacrament his body, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while fleſh and blood, othervvhile bread, with the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral nature whereof, according to theſe viſible things, he hath communicate the portion of euerlaſting life. And againe, The ſacraments, as much as in them is, cannot be without their proper vertue, neither by any meanes doeth the diuine Maieſtie abſent it ſelfe from the myſteries. Theſe termes which <hi>Cyprian</hi> commonly vſeth, The diuine povver, The working of quickning, The effect of eternall life, The portion of life, The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſubſtance, The diuine Maieſtie, what other thing doe they ſet out to vs, then that which <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaid, that according to his Maieſtie, according to his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable and inuiſible grace, Chriſt is with vs euen vnto the end of the world, eſpecially ſince that he ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out the carnall ſenſe, and requireth a ſpirituall, as we haue in another place more fully expounded?</p>
            <p>Neither thought <hi>Cyrillus</hi> any othervviſe, writing in this ſort to <hi>Caloſyrius:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyril. ad Caloſ.</note> For that we ſhould not abhorre fleſh and blood being ſet vpon the holy Altars, God fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring our frailtie, putteth a force of life into thoſe things that be offered, turning them into the trueth of his proper fleſh, that a body of life, as it were a certaine quickning ſeed, may be found in vs. That trueth of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy which <hi>Cyprian</hi> calleth The working of quickning, The effect of eternall life, The portion of life, the ſame doth <hi>Cyrillus</hi> terme the force of life, a body of life, a quickening ſeed, meaning the ſpiritual power &amp; grace, as he expoundeth himſelfe vpon <hi>Iohn lib 4 ca. 17.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem in Ioan. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> ſaying thus: Euen as a little leauen (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) doth ſowre the whole lumpe, ſo a little bleſsing of God doth draw the whole man into himſelfe, and doth fill him with his grace, and in this ſort doeth Chriſt abide in vs, and we in Chriſt. By this meanes he reiecteth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:1338:46"/>
is to ſay, the eating of mans fleſh, and withdraweth the minds of the faithfull from vntrue meanings &amp; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoughts, and affirmeth to <hi>Euoptius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem ad Euopt.</note> that this myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is receiued in an onely pure and exquiſite faith, as we haue mentioned before. For it is neceſſary that ſuch an eating be ſpirituall and made by grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Athanaſius</hi> was of this opinion.<note place="margin">Athanaſ. de Pecca. in Spiri. Sanct.</note> In his booke of the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt he writeth in this ſort: For this cauſe made hee mention of the Aſcenſion of the Sonne of man into Heauen, that hee might withdraw them from a corporall imagination, &amp; that they might afterward learne, that the heauenly meate that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from aboue, and the ſpirituall food which he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, is called the fleſh of Chriſt. For, <hi>the wordes that I haue ſpoken to you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>be Spirit and life.</hi> Which is aſmuch as if he ſhould ſay, The body which is ſhewed and ſlaine, ſhalbe giuen for the food of the world, that it may be ſpiritually diſtributed in euery one, and bee made a preſeruation for all to the reſurrection of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. For this cauſe (ſayeth <hi>Athanaſius</hi>) mention was made of the Aſcenſion of the Sonne of man, that he might call vs away from corporall imagining of his preſence, and might aftervvard learne that the grace, or ſpirituall povver which he termeth the heauenly meat comming from aboue, and ſpirituall food, and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that it is ſpiritually diſtributed, is called the fleſh of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>To theſe agreeth <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vpon <hi>Matthew cap. 26.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſost. in Matth. cap. <hi>26.</hi> Homil. <hi>83.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hom. 83.</hi> Will ye not ſee (ſaith he) with what a cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of minde Infants doe ſnatch the breaſt, with what appreſsing do they faſten their lips to the nipples? Let vs with no leſſe deſire come alſo to this Table, and ſpirituall nipple of this cup, yea rather with a greater coueting let vs (like ſucking babes) ſucke the grace of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:1338:47"/>
the Spirit:<note place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note> Let vs haue one griefe and heauineſſe of heart, if we be depriued of this ſpirituall food. The ſame man in the ſame Homily ſaith, That it is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible thing which is giuen vs in this ſacrament, but by things ſenſible, euen as in Baptiſme. Theſe be the words: Since therefore he ſaith, <hi>This is my body,</hi> let vs haue no doubt, but beleeue, and behold it with our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. For no ſenſible thing is deliuered vs from Chriſt, but by ſenſible things, and yet all things which he deliuered be inſenſible. So alſo in Baptiſme, by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which is a ſenſible thing, that gift is granted: but that which is wrought in it, (namely regeneration and renuing) is a certaine intelligible thing. For if thou haddeſt bene without a body, hee would haue giuen thee the gifts barely without body: but becauſe thy ſoule is ioyned to a body, in ſenſible, things to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood are giuen thee. O hovv many do now a daies ſay, I would I might ſee his forme and ſhape, I would I might ſee his garments, alſo his ſhooes I would I might ſee. Thou doeſt therefore ſee him, touch him, eat him; thou deſireſt but to ſee his garments, but he giueth thee himſelfe, not only that thou maieſt ſee him, but maieſt touch him and haue him in thee. <hi>Chryſostom</hi> doth here command vs to beleeue Chriſt, vvhen he ſaith, <hi>This is my body,</hi> but to behold it with the eyes of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: For he ſaith, that neither any ſenſible or bodily thing is giuen in the ſacraments, but by thoſe things that be ſenſible, the very gifts to be vnderſtood, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporall are giuen vs; and that not onely in Baptiſme, but alſo in the Supper of the Lord. But if Chriſt do giue vs himſelfe in his Supper, and yet no bodily thing is giuen, (for he ſaith that the gifts be incorporall) It is manifeſt that <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> doth agree with the reſt of the Fathers, that Chriſt is preſent in the vſe of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:1338:47"/>
by grace and vertue of his body. And although this Author doe vſe in ſome places deuout <hi>Hyperboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> ſpeeches diſputing of this ſacrament, which thing he hath alſo done here, when hee affirmeth that Chriſt is ſet before vs, not only to be ſeene, but alſo to be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: yet an indifferent reader may eaſily perceiue by this place and ſome other,<note place="margin">Theodoritus Dial. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> what was his right opinion of this matter. The very ſame thing doth <hi>Theodoritus</hi> plainely teach in his firſt Dialogue, in this wiſe;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ortho.</hi> Our Sauiour himſelfe chaunged the names, and gaue the name of the figure to his bodie, and the name of his bodie to the figure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sodal.</hi> Thou ſaieſt true: but I would learne the cauſe of this change of names.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ortho.</hi> The cauſe is plaine to them that bee inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the heauenly myſteries: for his will was, that they which partake the heauenly myſteries, ſhould giue no heed to the nature of the thinges which bee ſeene, but by the change of names they ſhould beleeue the alteration that is made by grace: for he which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had called his naturall body meat and bread, and againe calleth himſelfe a Vine, the ſame hath honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the figures which be ſeene, with the title of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and blood, not altering the nature, but ioyning grace to the nature. Nothing can bee ſpoken more plainely then <hi>Theodoritus</hi> doth here expounde, how bread is the body of Chriſt, that is to ſay, becauſe the nature of bread remaineth, and yet by grace is made his bodie, in that grace is ioyned to the nature of the bread. The ſame man <hi>Dial. 2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem Dial. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> For neither doe the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall ſignes, after the ſanctification, depart from their proper nature, for they tarie in their former ſubſtance, ſhape and forme, and may bee ſeene and touched euen as before: but they be vnderſtood to be the things that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:1338:48"/>
they bee made, and ſo beleeued and worſhipped, as though they were the ſame which they be beleeued. He ſaid before, that the nature of the ſignes did remaine, but that there was a change made by grace; that the nature was not changed, but that grace was ioyned. Here doth he plainely ſay, that the ſubſtance, faſhion and forme of the outward figures bee the ſame after ſanctification, that they were: but yet they be made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things to our vnderſtanding and faith, that is to ſay, by grace as he taught vs before, ſinging al one ſong with <hi>Chriſostome,</hi> That no ſenſible or corporate thing is here giuen, but that they bee things intelligible, and incorporate, which be giuen by grace and with vertue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Euthymius in Matth. cap. <hi>64.</hi>
               </note>Hereunto appertaine the words of <hi>Euthymius</hi> vpon <hi>Matthew chap. 64.</hi> Therefore euen as the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had ſacrifices and blood, ſo hath the new alſo, namely the body and blood of the Lord: for hee ſaide not, Theſe bee ſignes of my body, but, Theſe bee my body &amp; my blood. Therfore we muſt not take heed to the nature of thoſe things which bee ſet before vs, but to the vertue of them. For euen as aboue nature, hee deified the fleſh that was taken of the Virgin, if it bee lawful to vſe this phraſe; ſo alſo doth he vnſpeakeably change theſe things into his verie liuely body, and into his verie precious blood, and into the grace of them. In that hee ſaith, Wee may not regard the nature of thoſe things that be ſet before vs, he teacheth that the nature of the bread remaineth: and in that hee addeth, But to the vertue of them, hee ſheweth that by vertue they be the body of Chriſt, and not by any carnall meanes. Finallie he addeth by interpretation, And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the grace of them, that hee might exclude carnall imaginations.<note place="margin">Leo &amp; Synod. Ro. de con. diſt. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Leo</hi> and the Synode of Rome <hi>de conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. Diſt. 2.</hi> doe not differ from theſe: for thus bee the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:1338:48"/>
words: Becauſe in that myſticall diſtribution of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall food, this is giuen, and this is receiued, that wee receiuing the vertue of this heauenly meate, may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his fleſh which was made our fleſh. You haue almoſt the very words which <hi>Emiſſenus</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vſed, as we rehearſed before, The diſtribution of the heauenly food, the vertue of the heauenly meate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and that ſo we become his fleſh. What other thing is this, then that wee be ioyned with his fleſh by grace and vertue? For how can we otherwiſe be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into his fleſh?</p>
            <p>To this tendeth alſo the ſaying of <hi>Hilary</hi> there brought in among other:<note place="margin">Hilarius.</note> For the viſible quantitie is not to be eſteemed in this myſterie, but the vertue of the ſpirituall ſacrament. Moreouer <hi>Theophylactus,</hi> which is counted as it were a certaine follower and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> doth affirme this moſt plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as we haue aboue more fully ſet foorth: out of the which I will repeate a few thinges here; the reſt, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, thou maiſt thy ſelfe take out of him. For both he taketh vtterly away carnal imaginations, and affirmeth that the words of this myſterie are ſpiritually to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, as thoſe which haue no things carnall, but bring euerlaſting life: and he ſheweth the manner and way how to vnderſtand them writing in this wiſe. And how (ſaith he) is not fleſh ſeene? O man,<note place="margin">Thoph. in Mar. cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> this is done for our infirmitie: for inſomuch as the bread and wine be of thoſe things which we be acquainted withall, we abhorre them not: but if we ſhould ſee blood and fleſh ſet before vs, we could not abide it, but ſhould abhorre it. Therefore God of his mercie fauoring our frailtie, retaineth ſtill the forme of bread &amp; wine, but he chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the creatures into the power of fleſh and blood. The ſame man <hi>in Ioan. cap 6.</hi> vpon theſe words,<note place="margin">Idem in Ioan. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>This is
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:1338:49"/>
a hard ſaying, who can away withall? &amp;c.</hi> See their follie: for their dutie had been to haue asked &amp; learned thoſe thinges whereof they were ignorant: but they ſtarted backe, and did conſtrue nothing ſpiritually, but all things as they outwardly appeared: For when they heard of fleſh, they thought hee would compell them to be deuourers of fleſh and blood. But becauſe wee vnderſtand it ſpiritually, neither wee be deuourers of fleſh, and yet we be ſanctified by ſuch meat. The opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Theophylactus</hi> is certaine, that the faithfull be not in the ſacrament <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, deuourers of fleſh, as I may ſo terme it, as the letter properly ſoundeth: but that ſpirituall ſence is required, that is, the forme of bread &amp; wine being retained, the vertue of his fleſh and blood is receiued of the faithfull, as it is manifeſt by his owne words both here and thoſe before rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.<note place="margin">Bertram.</note> Wherefore <hi>Bertram</hi> following the opinion of the old Fathers, hath thus written: For according to the ſubſtance of the creatures, they be the ſame alſo after, that they were before the conſecration. They were before bread and wine, in which forme being now conſecrated they ſeeme to remaine. Therfore is there a thing changed inwardly by the mightie power of the holy Ghoſt, which faith beholdeth, and feedeth the ſoule, and miniſtreth ſubſtance of eternall life. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: But now, becauſe faith doeth behold that whole, whatſoeuer that whole is, and the eye of the fleſh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth nothing, ye ſhall vnderſtand that thoſe things which be ſeene, be the bodie and blood Chriſt, not in forme but in ſtrength. The ſame <hi>Bertram</hi> when he had rehearſed this ſaying of <hi>Iſidore:</hi> Which thinges for that cauſe be called ſacraments, becauſe vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of corporall things, the diuine power doth worke more ſecret ſaluation, whereupon they be called ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:1338:49"/>
alſo, of their ſecret and holie vertues, and in Greek it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> becauſe it hath a ſecret &amp; hid di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation. And after he addeth of his own this ſaying: What be we taught therby, but that the body &amp; blood of the Lord be for that cauſe called Myſteries, becauſe they haue a ſecret and hid diſpenſation, that is, they be one thing which they outwardly betoken, and another which inwardly they inuiſibly worke? Of this alſo they be called ſacraments, becauſe vnder the couer of corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall things, the diuine power doth more ſecretly mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the ſaluation of thoſe that receiue them faithfully. By all theſe things which haue hitherto bene ſpoken it hath bene made manifeſt, that the body and blood of Chriſt which in the Church be receiued by the mouth of the faithfull, bee figures, according to their viſible forme; but according to their inuiſible ſubſtance, that is, the power of the heauenly Word, they verily be the body and blood of Chriſt. Whereupon, according to the viſible creature they feed the body, but according to the vertue of their better ſubſtance, they both feed and ſanctifie the minds of the faithfull. Theſe bee <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trams</hi> words.</p>
            <p>Hitherto haue we declared, what hath bene the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the old true diuines of the Supper of the Lord, aſwell Grecians as Latines, euen vnto <hi>Bertrams</hi> time, who in the yeere after Chriſts birth 840. was a famous man both in life &amp; learning, noted by no man of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, nor found fault with as hauing ill written, but great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly praiſed by the iudgement of learned and good men. Wherefore that <hi>Iohn,</hi> called <hi>Abbas Trithemius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Abbas Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them.</note> doubted not to reckon him in the roule of diuine &amp; famous wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and to praiſe him by this his teſtimony that folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: <hi>Bertram</hi> an Elder and Monke very expert in holy Scripture, and notably wel learned in humanitie, quick
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:1338:50"/>
of wit, eloquent of ſpeech, no leſſe famous in life then learning, writ many notable little treatiſes, whereof a few haue come to my knowledge. He writ one booke of Predeſtination, a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable worke: To <hi>Charles</hi> the king, brother to <hi>Lotharius</hi> the Emperor, of the body and blood of the Lord, another booke. Theſe things haue I the more willingly rehearſed, to this intent, to reproue that railing boldnes of tongue that ſome man hath v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, who in a book newly ſet forth of this controuerſie, when he had nothing wherewith he could anſwer <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram,</hi> thought it ſufficient to deſpiſe this ſo famous a man, &amp; to note him with the name of an heretike. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram,</hi> ſaith he, or what other ſoeuer was author of that worke ſet forth in his name, was a crafty and an impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Heretike. O ſhameles face and meet to be bridled! <hi>Barnard</hi> alſo which liued 300. yeere after <hi>Bertram,</hi> doth reiect all carnall vnderſtanding in the wordes of the Lords Supper, and acknowledgeth onely a ſpirituall; whoſe words, taken out of his Sermon in the day of the Lords Supper, I haue here added: A ſacrament is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a holy ſigne, or holy ſecret. Many things certainly be done only for themſelues: ſome other alſo for other things betokened: and they be called ſignes, and be ſo. As for example of vſual matters, a ring is giuen abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely for a ring, &amp; there is no ſignification: It is giuen to ſet a man in poſſeſsion of any eſtate of inheritance, and it is a token: ſo that now he that receiueth it, may ſay, the ring is of ſmal value, but it is the inheritance that I ſeeke. After this ſort therefore our Lord drawing neere his Paſsion, was careful to ſet his diſciples in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion of his grace, that his inuiſible grace might be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by ſome viſible ſigne. To this intent hee ordained the ſacraments.<note place="margin">Idem de S. Mart.</note> To this end is the partaking of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Thankeſgiuing. The ſame man of <hi>S. Martin:</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:1338:50"/>
Without faile euen vnto this day is the ſame fleſh gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs, but ſpiritually, not carnally: neither haue we to finde fault that there is denied to this our time, the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing which was ſhewed to the Fathers of the olde Teſtament, or that preſence of his fleſh which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to the Apoſtles: For certainely, neither of both can be prooued to be wanting to thoſe that conſider it faithfully. For the true ſubſtance of his fleſh is alſo now preſent with vs no doubt, but in a ſacrament, and there be reuelations, but yet in ſpirit and povver: ſo that no part of grace can be prooued to be wanting in the time of grace that now is. In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion, neither the eye hath ſeene, nor the eare hath heard, neither haue they aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into the heart of man, which God hath prepared for them that loue him. Notwithſtanding, he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiled them vnto vs by his Spirit. Neither marueile thou, that he gaue carnal apparances vnto them which looked for his carnall comming: for it is neceſſary that we haue the grace ſo much more of force, &amp; the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of more dignitie, as thoſe things vndoubtedly be more excellent that we looke for. It cannot be hid by theſe things that we haue ſpoken, what was <hi>Bernards</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the preſence of the fleſh in the Lords Supper. Firſt, folowing the old writers, he appointeth two parts of the ſacrament: the outward ſigne, and the invvard matter, which he defineth to be inuiſible grace. Againe, the fleſh is giuen to vs, but ſpiritually, not carnally. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, that the very ſubſtance of his fleſh is preſent, but yet as it is fit for the time of grace, in grace, ſpirit and povver. As for that other Sermon of the Supper of the Lord, ſince it is not reckoned among <hi>Bernards</hi> owne works, albeit it be not contrary to theſe things that we haue now ſpoken, (if ſo be the author be thought to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with himſelfe) yet ſince it is counted another mans
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:1338:51"/>
worke, &amp; to haue a falſe title, it ought not to take place in a controuerſie of ſo great a matter. Therefore in this third part of this worke I meant to ſhew, &amp; I thinke I haue ſo done, how Chriſt our Lord ought to be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be preſent in the adminiſtration of his holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, according to common &amp; agreeable interpretations of the ancient Fathers. Firſt I taught, that a ſpirituall vnderſtanding of eating the fleſh of Chriſt was required by them, and all carnal imagination aboliſhed. Then, that it was no ſpiritual maner of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, if a man folow the letter, and proper ſignification of the words, ſuch as they fained which brought in Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or doe appoint a groſſe preſence of fleſh with the bread, but that all ſuch imaginations be carnall and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, &amp; not ſpiritual. Laſtly, what thoſe Fathers dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſpirituall vnderſtanding, namely that the body of Chriſt in the ſacrament of Thankeſgiuing, is giuen to the faithfull by grace and effectual povver, in a certaine holy ſigne.</p>
            <p>But here a doubt riſeth. If we beleeue that the grace and vertue of his true body bee ioyned with the bread and wine, wee ſhall ſeeme to attribute too much to the Elements, &amp; therof ſhould come a double euil: for ſo it ſhall come to paſſe, that the worſhipping of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will follow, &amp; the perill of idolatrie; &amp; euill men when they receiue the ſacrament ſhould alſo eate his body, &amp; be partakers of his grace. But that cannot be. <hi>He that eateth me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>he ſhall liue for me, and hee that eateth this bread ſhall liue for euer:</hi> which cannot bee vnderſtood of ill men. As concerning the worſhipping of the ſacrament, I anſwere, that the ancient fathers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the ſacrament of thankſ-giuing with reuerence and great honor, &amp; yet for all that, were ſafe from ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie; which thing might alſo happen to vs, if the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:1338:51"/>
diſcipline were reuoked,<note place="margin">August. in Pſal. <hi>98.</hi>
               </note> &amp; the maner of Catechiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me reſtored. For <hi>Augustin</hi> doth euidently teach in <hi>Pſal. 98.</hi> when he ſaith, That the ancient fathers worſhipped when they did receiue. He gaue you his very fleſh to be eaten for ſaluation: but none eateth that fleſh vnles he haue firſt worſhipped. And we do not only not offend in worſhipping, but we offend in not worſhipping. The ſame man in <hi>Sent. Proſperi:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem in Sent. Proſp.</note> But we in the forme of bread and wine which wee ſee, doe honour inuiſible things, namely fleſh and blood. Likewiſe <hi>Euſebius Emiſſenus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. Emiſſ.</note> When thou goeſt vp to the holy Altar to bee fed with the ſpirituall food, behold in thy faith the holy bodie and blood of thy God, honour it, eſteeme it greatly. And <hi>Chryſostome 1 Cor. 10. Homilia 24:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſost.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>Hom.</hi> 24.</note> For I will ſhew thee that on earth, which is worthy of greateſt honor. For euen as in Kings pallaces, not the walles, not the goulden roofe, but the body of a King ſitting in his throne, is the excellenteſt of al: ſo is alſo in heauen, the body of the king, which is now ſet before thee to bee ſeene in earth: I ſhew thee neither Angels, nor Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels, nor the hie heauens, but the Lord of all them. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> vpon the <hi>1. Cor. 11.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> The ſacrament of thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing is a ſpirituall medicine, which being taſted with reuerence doth purifie a deuout mind. And by and by he teacheth, that we muſt come with a deuout minde, and with feare to the holy Communion, that the mind may know, that it oweth a reuerence to him whoſe body it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to receiue. <hi>Theodorit</hi> alſo <hi>dial. 2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theodoritus Dial. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do the myſtical ſignes after the ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> depart from their proper nature; for they remaine in their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſubſtance, ſhape &amp; faſhion, and may be both ſeene and touched euen as before: but the things which they be made, be vnderſtood, and beleeued, &amp; worſhipped, as if they were the ſelf things which they be beleeued.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:1338:52"/>By this and other places, it is eaſie to perceiue, with what honor, &amp; with what reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the ancient fathers came to the holy Communion. Neyther is it any mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, ſince they beleeued that they receiued in that bread, the true nature, and vertue of our Lords true body, and were farre off from idolatrie, being inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and diligently taught, not to worſhip the outward ſigne, but the inward vertue. Which thing <hi>Auguſtin</hi> declareth by theſe wordes,<note place="margin">August. de doct. Christ. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>De doctrina Chriſtiana lib. 3. cap. 9.</hi> For he ſerueth vnder a ſigne, which worketh or reuerenceth any thing that ſignifieth, not knowing what it ſignifieth: but he that either worketh or reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renceth a profitable ſigne ordained of God, whoſe force and ſignification he vnderſtandeth, doth not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor this that is ſeene and paſſeth away, but rather that whereunto all ſuch things be referred. And ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: But in this time, after that by the reſurrection of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt the moſt manifeſt iudgement of our libertie appeared, we haue not bene laden with the weightie operation of thoſe ſignes which we now vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand: but the Lord himſelfe, &amp; the doctrine of the Apoſtles hath deliuered vnto vs a few in ſteed of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and thoſe verie eaſie to be done, &amp; moſt pure to be kept; namely the ſacrament of Baptiſme, and the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the body &amp; blood of our Lord, which eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man when he receiueth, being inſtructed, he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth whereto they be applied, ſo that he doth reuerence them not with a carnal ſeruitude, but rather with a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall liberty. Here wee ſee with what learning the Chriſtian men in time paſt were ſeaſoned, before they ſhould come to the vſe of the ſacraments; and how, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they honored or worſhipped aſwell in Baptiſme as in the celebration of the Supper, yet that was done without perill or offence. Perill, as here it is euident,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:1338:52"/>
when as they had no reſpect to that which is ſeene and doth decay, but to the vertue and ſignification therof: Offence, becauſe they had a conſcience in time paſt, I will not ſay to receiue the ſacraments before Infidels, and ſuch as were ignorant of the myſteries, but not ſo much as to talke of ſo ſecret matters before them. Of the which thing there be many teſtimonies: but wee wil for this time be content with this one, taken out of the <hi>2. Dial.</hi> of <hi>Theodoritus.</hi> For <hi>Orthodoxus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dial. <hi>2.</hi> Theod.</note> being asked how he before the conſecration called that which was offered by the Prieſt, anſwered, We muſt not ſpeake frankely: for it is likely that there be ſome here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent which be not inſtructed in the myſteries of Chriſt. <hi>Eran.</hi> Anſwere mee therefore ſoftlie. By this place it is euident, how warily, and ſoberly they in time paſt ſpake of the myſteries. And this is worth the labour to note, That the ancient writers, when they ſpake of the ſacraments, did vſe diuers termes of honoring, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerencing, or worſhipping: By the which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding either they meant to ſignifie ſome other honour and reuerence meet for holy matters, then that which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded of God when he ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue.</hi> So that worſhipping may be defined to bee of two ſorts: the one, wherewith we worſhip God himſelfe: The other, wherewith we worſhip the preſcribed ſignes &amp; diuine myſteries, according to that ſaying, <hi>Worſhip yee his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole:</hi> which thing moſt men vnderſtand to be ſpoken of the arke of couenant: other interpret it to be of the humanitie of Chriſt. Or admit that there is one man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of worſhipping in both places, wee might ſay, that the fleſh of Chriſt is to be worſhipped, though it bee a creature, for the diuinitie ioyned therewith; that the arke of couenant was to be worſhipped, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:1338:53"/>
of the diuine maieſtie, which God himſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ſhould be there preſent. After the which ſort al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo we may worſhip the ſacrament of Thankeſ-giuing for the vnſpeakeable and inuiſible grace of Chriſt ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therewith, as <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith, not honouring that which is ſeene and paſſeth away, but that which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued and vnderſtood. This alſo is worthy to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, that the worſhip in old time, was not done by the idle lookers on, but by them which did receiue the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and were made partakers of their grace. For he that worſhippeth &amp; receiueth, to him it is the body of Chriſt; not to him that worſhippeth &amp; receiueth not. For to this intent was that meat ordained, that wee worſhipping ſhould eate, and not that wee ſhould wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it when others eate. Thus much bee ſaid concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the worſhipping. But in that it is denied that euill men can eate the body of Chriſt, which thing ſhould neceſſarily be done, if the ſpirituall vertue &amp; grace be ioyned with the bread; it may be anſwered, That there is a diſtinction to be vſed. For if we haue regard to the very nature of the ſacrament, the diuine povver can by no meanes be abſent from the ſigne, in that it is a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; ſerueth to that vſe: but if we regard the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners &amp; inclination of the receiuer, it is not life &amp; grace to him, vvhich othervviſe of the ovvne nature is both, becauſe the vvickedneſſe of euill men cannot be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of ſo great a goodneſſe, &amp; ſuffereth it not to bring forth fruit, but contrariwiſe to them is it death &amp; dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. For euen as diuers kinds of meats bee of their owne nature wholeſome, but if they be put into diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed bodies, they increaſe the euill, and oftentimes ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten their time, not through their nature, but through the fault of the receiuer: ſo alſo commeth it to paſſe in the ſacrament, vvhoſe proper vertue is alvvayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:1338:53"/>
till it hath performed the office thereof, although an euil man when he receiueth it, cannot be partaker of ſo great goodneſſe, nor perceiue any fruit thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cyprian de Coena Domini</hi> confirmeth the very ſame.<note place="margin">Cyprian. de Coena Dom.</note> The ſacraments truely, ſaith he, as much as in them is, cannot be without their proper vertue, neither by any meanes doth the diuine Maieſtie abſent it ſelfe from the myſteries. But albeit the ſacraments permit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be receiued or touched of vnworthy perſons; yet for all that they cannot be partakers of the Spirit, whoſe infidelitie or vnworthines doth reſiſt to ſo great an holineſſe. And therefore theſe gifts to ſome be a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of life to life, and to ſome a ſauour of death vnto death: For it is altogether right, that the deſpiſers of grace be depriued of ſo great a benefit, that the puritie of ſo great grace ſhould haue no dwelling in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy. <hi>Augustin</hi> againſt the letters of <hi>Petiliane lib. 2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">August. cont. literas Petill. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>47.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ca. 47.</hi> Therefore remember that the maners of ill men do nothing hurt the ſacraments of God, to make that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be not ſacraments at all, or be leſſe holy: but the hurt is to the ill men themſelues, that they ſhould haue them for a teſtimony of damnation, and not for a helpe to ſaluation. The ſame man in his fift booke of Baptiſme <hi>Contra Donatiſtas cap. 8.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem de Bapt. lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> For euen as <hi>Iudas</hi> to whom the Lord gaue a ſop, made place for the deuil in himſelfe, not by receiuing that which was euil, but by ill receiuing it; So euery man that receiueth vnworthily the ſacrament of the Lord, maketh it not euill becauſe he is euill, or that he receiue nothing, becauſe he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it not to his ſaluation. For it was the body of the Lord, &amp; the blood of the Lord alſo to them, to whom the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>He that eateth vnworthily,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem contra Creſcen. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>eateth &amp; drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his owne iudgement.</hi> The ſame man <hi>contra Creſcen. lib. 1. cap. 25.</hi> Albeit the Lord himſelfe ſay, <hi>Vnleſſe a man
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:1338:54"/>
eate my fleſh, and drinke my blood, he ſhall haue no life in him,</hi> doth not the ſame Apoſtle teach, that this becommeth deſtruction to them that vſe it ill? For he ſaith, <hi>He that eateth the bread, and drinketh of the cup of the Lord vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, is guilty of the body and blood of the Lord.</hi> Behold, how diuine and holy myſteries do hurt thoſe that vſe them ill. Why not Baptiſme in like maner? By theſe &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other places it is euident, that the ſacrament of Thankeſgiuing, aſmuch as pertaineth to the nature of the ſacrament, is verily the body and blood of Chriſt, and is verily a diuine and holy thing, albeit it be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the vnvvorthy: where notwithſtanding they be not made partakers of the grace, &amp; holines thereof, but they draw thereout death and damnation. For neither doth ſo great a goodnes remaine in them, or enter into them, to the intent to remaine, but to condemne them. Neither doeth the touching of the Lords body any more profit them, then it did the <hi>Iewes</hi> that crucified Chriſt, to touch his body that was hallowed, &amp; alwaies indued with his grace. Wherefore let this be certaine, that the ſacraments, as long as they be ſacraments, doe retaine their vertue, neither can they be ſeparated from it. For they alwayes conſiſt of their parts, heauenly and earthly, viſible and inuiſible, inward &amp; outvvard, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good men or euill, worthy or vnvvorthy receiue them. And alſo that change of ſignes and paſſage of elements into the invvard ſubſtance, which wee often find in the old writers, can by no meanes ſtand, if we ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate the vertue from the ſigne, or would haue the one receiued apart from the other. But this is ſo to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, as long as the ſigne ſerueth to that vſe, and is applied to that end for the which it was ordained, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods word. For if we apply it to other vſes, and abuſe it contrary to Chriſts inſtitution; either it is
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:1338:54"/>
no ſacrament at all, or elſe it ceaſeth from being a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Therefore they commit no light offence, which do not direct the ſignes of bread and wine to that end which Chriſt ordained them for, but do conſecrat them for a pompe, farre off from Gods word, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding doe thruſt them to the ſimple people in ſtead of ſacraments. For although they be miniſtred or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, and according to their lavvfull vſe; yet when that vſe and doing of their proper office doeth ceaſe, they retaine no longer neither the name, nor vertue of ſacraments, which thing the old cuſtome of the church doeth proue. For when the Communion was ended, men did eat their common ſupper, and ſpent together in the Church thoſe things that remained of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as <hi>Hierom</hi> doth witneſſe vpon the <hi>1. Cor. cap. 11.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hlerom in <hi>1.</hi> Cor. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> And partly thoſe things that remained vnſpent, vvere ſtreightway caſt in the fire,<note place="margin">Heſych. in Leui. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Heſychius</hi> teacheth <hi>In Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. lib. 2. cap. 8.</hi> whereof neither was lawfull to be done, vnleſſe they had ceaſed to be ſacraments. Wherefore, neither is that doubt of them that receiue it vnvvorthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of any force to ſubuert this opinion which we haue ſet forth, but that neuertheleſſe remaineth ſafe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurt, and worthily to be imbraced of men deſirous of trueth and concord. Firſt, becauſe the dignitie &amp; due honour of the ſacraments is not hurt, but remaineth whole and vnblemiſhed, whileſt we confeſſe both the trueth of his body, and the nature and ſubſtance of the ſame, to be receiued of the faithfull together with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſignes, which thing the ancient Fathers do teſtifie to be done. Againe if we receiue that diſtinction which the ſame Fathers diligently obſerued, betvveene that proper aſſumpt body of the Lord, or that he tooke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and this figuratiue body, or ſacrament of his body, there is no offence committed againſt the rule of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:1338:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:1338:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:1338:56"/>
our faith, which by no meanes is to be wronged, ſince that we attribute to either body their due. For we ſay, that his proper and aſſumpt body is in a place, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted within the ſpace of a place, for the maner of his true body, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith: As the true maner of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature requireth, and the true beleeuing fathers againſt <hi>Marcion, Eutyches,</hi> and other heretikes do ſtoutly affirme; Which thing they that deny, and appoint that body to be euery where, doe by that meanes deny the true nature of his body, and fall into the errors and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies of them. And yet there is no let, but the trueth of his myſticall body, becauſe it is a ſpirituall and diuine matter, is as largely ſpread &amp; preſent, as the celebration of the ſacrament is ſpread, according to the opinion of the ſame true beleeuing Fathers. Furthermore, no ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities follow this doctrine, as very many doe inſue both that groſſe Tranſubſtantiation, &amp; alſo that carnal coupling with the bread; namely, that miſe, beaſts, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate men doe gnaw, chew, or ſwallow that precious body of the Lord which was taken of the Virgine, whereas it is lawfull for no man to eat of that body, no not for a godly man, as <hi>Hierom</hi> witneſſeth. Beſide, this is no doubtfull doctrine, nor hard to be perceiued, but open, and very cleare, as farre as the nature of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries do permit. And albeit this controuerſie doth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſeeme to many, intricate, and like a maze; this expoſition is eaſie, no darkenes in it, no wordes of the Scriptures, nor teſtimony of the Fathers be againſt it, but all they do agree &amp; friendly accord. Adde hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that this maner of handling this matter, is old, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly deliuered to vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ancient Fathers, not new ſprung, nor at this time firſt inuented, as the matter it ſelfe declareth; &amp; therefore it maketh them more friend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to obtaine the peace and tranquility of the Church,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:1338:56"/>
ſince that all men may vnderſtand that it is no new opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, made out of our owne heads, but the ancient opinion of the true beleeuing Fathers called to memory againe: eſpecially ſince it is of ſuch ſort as can iuſtly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend no part, but moue &amp; exhort all men to be content. There be ſome that take in ill part, that the ſacrament of Thankeſgiuing is called a ſigne or figure, as though it were a bare ſigne or vaine figure. Here they heare that it is not only a ſigne, but the thing it ſelfe, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a figure, but alſo the trueth. Not being contented herewith, they vrge the Fathers, they require the nature of his body in the ſacrament. Here alſo they do heare, that the preſence of his nature is taught, and that there is a naturall participation. Yet they goe further, and command vs to confeſſe a ſubſtance of his body. They ſee alſo that the ſubſtance is by vs affirmed to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and that our communion with Chriſt naturally and (if I may ſo ſay) ſubſtantially, is here ſet out: but yet that theſe termes ought to bee vnderſtood, not as Philoſophers, but as Diuines vſe to ſpeake. Neither would wee ſtriue ſo much about that terme of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, albeit it be barbarous &amp; nothing neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, if ſo be they would interpret it to be ſuch a change of ſubſtance as the ancient Fathers acknowledged, that is to ſay, a ſacramentall alteration; ſuch alſo as is made in a creature that is regenerat by Baptiſme, which is made a new man, and a new creature; and ſuch alſo as is made when wee be turned into the fleſh of Chriſt, which examples the ancient Fathers vſed. We do not ſo much eſchew the termes themſelues, although there is alſo reſpect to be had of them; but we require the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them, which the Fathers themſelues taught and earneſtly demaund; And onely that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is to ſay, the deuouring of fleſh, which by no meanes they
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:1338:57"/>
allow, but condemne as fooliſh and wicked, we reiect, as farre off from the Scriptures, and farre from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the Fathers, and finally directly ſtriuing with the true faith: and we iudge, that a ſpiritual mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is neceſſary in the eating of this fleſh, follovving therein Chriſt himſelfe the Author, and the conſent of the beſt allowed interpreters that we haue. Surely it is a marueilous matter to ſee, hovv in other controuerſies we be <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> men, and oftentimes take hold of diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions more curious then neceſſary: and in this diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Sacraments we admit no difference, we allow no equiuocation, although both the nature of the thing requireth it, and the authoritie of the old writers doe as it were point vs to it with a finger; and ſeeing that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Scriptures, nor the holy Fathers do ſpeake of the diuine myſteries after a naturall ſort, but after an high and diuine maner, as becommeth men that treat of diuine matters, and inſpired with God, comparing ſpiritual things with ſpirituall things. Againe, if there be any man that thinketh that there is here too much attributed to the elements, it is not ſo: but their due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence is giuen to the outward ſignes for the holy vſe of them. But the invvard povver which commeth by the force of the word of God, is onely that which the mind of the faithfull doth reſpect, which ſanctifieth the body and the minde of him that vſeth it. But if there be any that require a miracle, (for ſome of the Fathers called the ſacrament of Thankeſgiuing, a notable mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle) ſurely it is no leſſe to be marueiled at, that the bread and wine being earthly creatures, and ordeined to feed the body onely, doe poſſeſſe that force in them, and ſo mighty an efficacie by the vertue of the myſtical benediction, that they cleanſe, nouriſh, ſanctifie, and prepare to immortalitie both minds and bodies, ſo that
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:1338:57"/>
they make vs members of Chriſt, and one body with him. Yea this miracle hath more weight, more dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, greater profit, and more agreeable to the maner of the myſteries, then any groſſe Tranſubſtantiation, or naturall and humane fleſh-eating can comprehend. Wherefore, the ſeeds of contention and diſcord bee now taken away, and there remaineth no cauſe why, but the Churches of Chriſt, eſpecially thoſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the deſire of the Goſpel, may agree in one with quiet minds and coupled affections, which now diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree among themſelues with bitter hatred.</p>
            <p>Theſe things, my brethren, I haue thought meet to gather together touching this controuerſie full of thornes, as it ſeemed to many: ſurely at the firſt not with this intent to ſet it abroad in print, but to haue ſome certaintie whereto I may leane, in a matter ſo full of controuerſie, and yeeld a reaſon of my opinion. But now, that me thinketh I haue taken ſome fruit of this worke, vvhateuer it bee, I am not vnwilling if it may bring any profit to others alſo. This I know in my owne conſcience, that I haue ſought for no other thing in this Treatie, but godly and modeſtly to profit my ſelfe and others.</p>
            <p>I beſeech the GOD and Father of our Lord IESVS CHRIST to remooue from the mindes of Paſtours, Doctours and Miniſters of the Church, the greateſt confuſion of the Church, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſtriue and rule, and diſpoſe their mindes to peace and brotherly concord in Chriſt, that they may not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe this notable bond of loue, deliuered and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by the Lord himſelfe to his Church, wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to the nouriſhing of contentions and factions: And vouchſafe to inſpire with his Spirit the hearts of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:1338:58"/>
Princes and Magiſtrates, that they may aboue all things regard what doeth moſt become the rule com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their charge, and aduance Gods glory, and not reſpect vvhat may grovv to their coffers by this troubleſome time, with the cruell vexation of their Subiects, and common cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of their Common-weales.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1338:58"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
